<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: fiction | Echo and Bounce]]></title>
  <link href="http://life.mumak.net/blog/categories/fiction/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://life.mumak.net/"/>
  <updated>2013-09-15T14:19:46+01:00</updated>
  <id>http://life.mumak.net/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Jonathan Lange]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Indifference]]></title>
    <link href="http://life.mumak.net/2013/05/indifference.html"/>
    <updated>2013-05-05T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://life.mumak.net/2013/05/indifference</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<div class='post'>
Arnold the Wanderer reclined back in his chair, hugging a hot cup of tea with his hands. &nbsp;It wasn't as he normally liked it, but it was hot, and that was an important thing. "It's not that I'm at all ungrateful for your hospitality," he said, "but what or who exactly is this temple for?"<br /><br />The monk's face lit up with a special glee. "Oh, no, not at all. &nbsp;We welcome the chance to share the particularities of our message with any who earnestly seek the path".<br /><br />"I wouldn't quite call myself a seeker, you know. Just a fellow who's a bit baffled."<br /><br />"Ah, yes," the monk spread his hands and smiled, relishing a rare chance to nod sagely, "all too well do I remember the confusion of the unenlightened."<br /><br />"No, no – well, yes, maybe – but what religion are you?"<br /><br />"We are the followers of Bel Shang-Gur, and we strive to walk in his path."<br /><br />Arnold had wandered the earth for years, and had spoken to many mystics, demagogues, hermits, hierophants and sarcedotes. He had never heard of Bel Shang-Gur, and said as much.<br /><br />"Bel Shang-Gur was originally not a holy man, but a prosperous merchant in a city far south of here. One afternoon, as he was walking down its streets, arm in arm with his wife, she, in her ignorance, asked him the First Unanswerable Question, planting the seed of our whole order.<br /><br />'What would you like to do tonight?'<br /><br />As Bel Shang-Gur heard those words, he saw a single blossom fall from one of the linden trees that lined the street. Although he had heard those words hundreds of times before, a new and spiritual understanding dawned within him.<br /><br />'I don't know, what would you like to do?'<br /><br />On instinct! So early! Simple words, and yet so profound! He had discovered the Second Unanswerable Question, the second vertex of the mystery on which our order is founded."<br /><br />Arnold the Wanderer did his best to nod sagely.<br /><br />"Does your neck trouble you, seeker?"<br /><br />"Uh, no. Carry on."<br /><br />The monk was frothing over like a glass of beer with a sugar cube in. "He saw that it was his will – to want or to not want – that divided him from the cosmos. That the blossom, resigned to its fate and carried by the wind was truly at peace. From that day forth, he resolved to cultivate an indifference to all things, and to pass on this serenity to all who would listen."<br /><br />"Here in Abbey of the Holy Apathy, we train ourselves to follow his path. First, we rid ourselves of preference and inclination, then anticipation and nostalgia, then appetite and desire, and finally attaining to a volitional void. &nbsp;'Blessed is he who truly doesn't mind either way'."<br /><br />"Truly, your way is an arduous one."<br /><br />"Oh yes! For the first year, our brother monks are instructed to mispronounce our names. It is only when the vexation is cleansed from our hearts that we are permitted to truly begin as novitiates."<br /><br />"And have you gone far on your journey to enlightenment?"<br /><br />The monk visibly slumped. "It is a hard path to walk. Just yesterday, I couldn't remember what I had for breakfast, which was a big step for me. I had porridge today though. Brother Kells most days can't remember whether he even had breakfast, the jammy bastard."<br /><br />Seeing Arnold's&nbsp;querulous&nbsp;gaze, the monk remembered himself and rose serenely. "Seeker, would you like another cup of tea?"<br /><br />"Oh, yes please! But could I have it with two sugars this time?" &nbsp;The monk's face turned ashen.<br /><br />"Dark indeed are the ways of the unenlightened."<br /><div><br /></div><span style="font-size: 13px;">This post is part of the&nbsp;</span><a href="http://life.mumak.net/2013/01/the-alphabet-supremacy.html" style="font-size: 13px;">Alphabet Supremacy</a><span style="font-size: 13px;">&nbsp;project, a collaboration between myself and&nbsp;</span><a href="http://life.metagnome.net/" style="font-size: 13px;">Bice Dibley</a><span style="font-size: 13px;">. Next week's word is Jubilee.</span></div>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Door]]></title>
    <link href="http://life.mumak.net/2013/02/door.html"/>
    <updated>2013-02-18T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://life.mumak.net/2013/02/door</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<div class='post'>
<i>Late, and I'm not at all happy with the result.</i>&nbsp;<i>However, <a href="https://twitter.com/metagnome/status/303298910263316480">Bice has called me on it</a>, so here it is.&nbsp;</i><br /><i><br /></i><i><br /></i><br />When Richard awoke, he was not in his bedroom, which was the customary place for him to rise. Nor was he in any bedroom that he recognized, although if you quizzed him on it, you would learn that there weren't that many that he could. Indeed was he not in any bedroom at all.<br /><br />Instead, he was in a sitting room, lying flat on the floor and staring at an ornate ceiling that appeared to be moving. &nbsp;This was not what he expected. The last thing he remembered was playing a friendly game of cards in the home of a well-to-do clergyman, or someone of that ilk.<br /><br />He peeled himself off the carpet, woozed lurchingly to his feet and looked around. &nbsp;The room was furnished in the older style, with an ornamental ceiling, too many chairs, and all of it in angry mustards and burgundies and pink pinstripes. &nbsp;It was enough to give one a headache.<br /><br />There weren't any windows to the room, which struck Richard as odd. &nbsp;There was a door though. &nbsp;It was a simple affair compared to the garish colours and &nbsp;patterns of the rest of the room. &nbsp;The handle had a curve chosen to match the crest of the chaise longue and the swooping legs of the chairs and tea tables that seemed to be everywhere in the room.<br /><br />And yet, whatever symmetry intended by the deranged mind behind the decor for the room was marred by the bulbous and ungainly body slumbering unquietly in the opposite corner.<br /><br />Richard quickly tried the handle. &nbsp;His memories of last night were only slowly returning to his fogged mind, but the snoring hillock of flesh in the corner was hard to forget. &nbsp;The door was locked, naturally. &nbsp;Some deep, reptilian reaction made him shake frantically at the handle, only to stop immediately as the more rational fear of waking the beast began to take hold.<br /><br />If only we were sooner gripped by our better doubts! &nbsp;The gelatinous mountain stirred, rising on its hind-quarters and emitting a bellow that rattled Richard's teeth.<br /><br />"Jacob, what a delight to see you", said Richard, demonstrating that he was not incapable of deceit.<br /><br />"Richard? Yes. Good. What time is it? Where's Smith? Right." Even at the best of times, Jacob tended to spare his interlocutor the difficulty of replying to his enquiries, and it appeared that immediately after rising was far from that. &nbsp;Richard tensed his legs, ready to run even though there was nowhere to run to. &nbsp;Any minute now, Jacob would remember.<br /><br />"You took my money".<br /><br />"Oh?", said Richard, as some answer seemed to be expected.<br /><br />"You took my money", Jacob repeated, wagging his finger -- which happened to be nearly the same size, shape and colour as an uncooked Cumberland sausage -- at Richard. &nbsp;As he said this, he stepped forward and knocked over one of the ridiculous chairs, its leg snapping under his heel.<br /><br />Richard edged back slowly toward the door. &nbsp;If one were given to a sort of narrow-minded, technical, hopelessly out-dated, moralistic way of putting things then, yes, one could say he had taken Jacob's money. &nbsp;Richard himself preferred to think that anyone who sat down to an obviously fixed game of cards instead gave him money. &nbsp;It implied a generosity of spirit that did Jacob credit.<br /><br />Still, occasionally one must sacrifice nobility of sentiment on the altar of rude circumstance. &nbsp;"I didn't <i>take</i> your money", Richard lied, "I was merely looking after it for you." &nbsp;He wouldn't fall for that, but perhaps it would delay the beating for long enough for someone to open this blasted door and rescue him.<br /><br />"Is that so? &nbsp;Well, return it to me now and I might even thank you for it." Richard didn't believe him, but reached for the winnings anyway. &nbsp;Desperate times and all that.<br /><br />It wasn't there. &nbsp;Richard stumbled sideways over a too dainty table, fell over and quivered back up again. &nbsp;"I don't have it on me". &nbsp;But where the hell was it? &nbsp;"Carrying that much lucre on my person would be both demeaning and foolhardy". &nbsp;After the game, his partner Smith had left, leaving him with the two they had just rinsed. &nbsp;Why had he done that? &nbsp;Jacob's hands were perilously close to his throat. &nbsp;"I was afraid that we would both fall to drink and so hid the money elsewhere, to protect it from our worser selves."<br /><br />"You took my money, and you lost it". &nbsp;Normally Richard would prize such clarity of thought.<br /><br />"No, I didn't lose it. &nbsp;Someone must have stolen it. &nbsp;Why else would we be imprisoned here?"<br /><br />Jacob looked confused, as if their situation had only just occurred to him. He went to the door to open it. &nbsp;The handle was tiny in his hands, but despite his turning, shaking, and pulling, the door remained firmly shut. &nbsp;He banged on the door, shouted and waited, yet no one answered.<br /><br />"You took my money, lost it, and trapped us both."<br /><br />"Well, we are both trapped together, although I do not know how it came to be, or even where we are."<br /><br />Even as he spoke, a key rattle in the lock. &nbsp;Richard spun around, and James orbited on his axis. &nbsp;The door began to open.<br /><div style="font-style: italic;"><br /></div><div style="font-style: italic;"><br /></div></div>


<h2>Comments</h2>


<div class='comments'>
<div class='comment'>
<div class='author'>JB<span class='comment-date'> on 2013-04-08 05:51</span></div>
<div class='content'>
I enjoyed it too. Perhaps we could get a Part II...</div>
</div>
<div class='comment'>
<div class='author'>Jonathan Lange<span class='comment-date'> on 2013-02-27 09:24</span></div>
<div class='content'>
Thank you for the kind words, I&#39;m very glad you liked it :)<br /><br />I still wish I had given myself enough time to actually finish it though.</div>
</div>
<div class='comment'>
<div class='author'>Mary<span class='comment-date'> on 2013-02-21 11:59</span></div>
<div class='content'>
I really like this, actually, although I can easily imagine how frustrating a piece it was to write.<br /><br />&quot;Richard himself preferred to think that anyone who sat down to an obviously fixed game of cards instead gave him money.  It implied a generosity of spirit that did Jacob credit.&quot; ← very nice.</div>
</div>
</div>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Bargain]]></title>
    <link href="http://life.mumak.net/2013/01/bargain.html"/>
    <updated>2013-01-20T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://life.mumak.net/2013/01/bargain</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<div class='post'>
<br />I wish I had someone to blame other than myself for me being out in this miserable weather. &nbsp;You would think by now that I would have the good sense not to hit Oxford Street during the January sales and the worst snow since America decided that it needed some space to pursue its own creative interests.<br /><br />I still haven't got used to the cold weather. &nbsp;I left my scarf at restaurant in Chinatown last week and I think I left one of my gloves at Mike's house last week. &nbsp;Every four or five steps I take my foot slips a little and I worry that this is going to be the end. &nbsp;Any second now I'm going to fall backwards on to the pavement and spend my last freezing moments being tsked over by busy shoppers for blocking the footpath.<br /><br />We're going to the opera tonight, you see. &nbsp;I've never been before but a quick search suggests that jeans and a hoodie might not be quite the thing. &nbsp;Although it runs against my cave troll chic, I actually do own a suit. &nbsp;I tried it on earlier today, to be on the safe side. &nbsp;My fashion tip: skin-tight three-quarter length pinstripes in the forthcoming frosty day in hell season.<br /><br />Which, rather appropriately, has left me staggering around London's busiest street with the tips of my fingers going numb and turning a slightly worrying shade of purple. &nbsp;Still, chin up old man, faint heart never won fair lady and all that. &nbsp;Oh look, churros.<br /><br />* * *<br /><br />The world -- slippery though it may be -- is a better place when nourished by deep-fried choux and chocolate sauce. &nbsp;Let remorse wait until tomorrow, for today I have pastry! &nbsp;Also, I think I've smeared some chocolate on my smart phone screen.<br /><br />There's apparently a men's suit shop a couple of blocks from here that's had some good reviews. &nbsp;I leave my warm, dougnutty haven and immediately almost slip over on the icey pavement. &nbsp;Only by frantically clutching the shoulders of a nearby stranger do I manage to stay upright. &nbsp;The little bugger seems upset with me. &nbsp;I don't know why. &nbsp;When I was eight I would have been proud to rescue an elder from certain calamity.<br /><br />The shop is called Taunton's. &nbsp;It's on a little side street that's just off a side street from Regent Street, down some all too slippery steps. &nbsp;The door opens and closes silently as I enter and air has a sort of musty closeness that reminds me of public libraries. &nbsp;At first I can't see anyone or even a counter, just racks of suits and shelves full of shirts and ties.<br /><br />I must have wandered in further than I thought, because I hear a voice behind me utter the terrifying words, "Excuse me, sir. &nbsp;May I help you?". &nbsp;I leap three feet into the air, spinning around and knocking over one of the racks in my surprise. &nbsp;I fumble a little while with the mess of jackets before the gentleman behind me reaches over and rights them. &nbsp;He is dressed in tweed and has a moustache that could have conquered Afghanistan for Queen Victoria.<br /><br />"May I help you, sir?", he asks again. &nbsp;I hate this question. &nbsp;I can never get the answer right.<br /><br />"Uhh, yes, I was wondering if you sell suits?" &nbsp;Oh bollocks. &nbsp;At least I can hope they give points for effort. &nbsp;He glances quickly around the shop as if to acknowledge that my doubt was valid and that no matter how damning the circumstances, the question bore further investigation.<br /><br />"We do indeed, sir. &nbsp;Is there a particular type of suit that sir is looking for?"<br /><br />"Well, I'm going to the opera tonight and I need--"<br /><br />"Ah yes sir, step right this way. &nbsp;I know just the thing to tempt you with." &nbsp;He walks with a slight limp, leading me around a table covered in silk handkerchiefs to a separate room. &nbsp;He notices me looking at his dragging foot, "I had a nasty fall a few years back" and winks as if I'm supposed to get the joke.<br /><br />"This, sir, is our finest gentleman's evening wear -- ideal for the opera." &nbsp;He gestures toward a mannequin dressed in the kind of dinner jacket that Bertie Wooster would have worn.<br /><br />"I'm not exactly sure. &nbsp;I mean, it does look a bit ... formal. &nbsp;I don't want to be over-dressed. &nbsp;It is only the ENO."<br /><br />"Sir, if you'll pardon me for saying so, as soon as you walk into the room wearing this, any other gentleman will be under-dressed." &nbsp;He measures me as he's speaking, and then produces a jacket, trousers, shirt and even shoes from various cupboards and drawers in the room.<br /><br />"Just try these on, sir, and see how they feel. I'll guarantee you'll never want anything else." &nbsp;He somehow guides me toward the change room with my arms full of expensive cloth. &nbsp; What is it about salesmen that makes me go invertebrate? &nbsp;"Oh, and sir ... ?" &nbsp;I turn around and he makes a sort of rubbing gesture on the side of his lip. &nbsp;I mimic him and feel some sticky chocolate sauce come off onto my finger. &nbsp;Oops.<br /><br />Anyway, I try on the suit and the devil is right, it does feel pretty good. &nbsp;How did he know my shoe size? &nbsp;As I leave I can feel a confidence in my step and a funny feeling in my shoulders that I can only guess is what not hunching feels like. (Cave troll, remember?)<br /><br />When I see myself in the mirror, I can hardly believe my eyes. &nbsp;I have never looked this good. &nbsp;Heck, I even look more clean shaven than I did in my street clothes.<br /><br />The salesman coughs politely. &nbsp;Although he is too tasteful to show it in his features, he has the air of a man who has finished the hardest part of a difficult job and finished it well. &nbsp; "How does that feel?", he asks. &nbsp;In my head, I say that I don't give a damn how it feels, it -- I -- look amazing, but I don't want to give the game away.<br /><br />"It's nice", I say. "How much is it?"<br /><br />"The suit, together with the shirt, waistcoat and shoes comes to £7,600." It's a little hard to breathe in here, was it always so hot? &nbsp;"Excluding VAT."<br /><br />I think I must have choked a little because the next thing I know the salesman is slapping me on the back and I'm coughing all over the place. &nbsp;As I come round, he steps back as if nothing had happened. &nbsp; "Of course, we also provide generous payment plans on instalments."<br /><br />I simply can't afford to spend that much money on a suit. &nbsp;I haven't spent that much money on anything ever. &nbsp;It's ridiculous even thinking about it, me even being here is ludicrous. &nbsp;But looking in the mirror it's so tempting. &nbsp;I look a million dollars, so paying only a few thousand pounds makes it a bargain, right?<br /><br />I can't believe I'm doing this, but I shrug my shoulders and nod. &nbsp;The gentleman leads me over to the sales counter where there's a contract waiting next to an ink bottle and quill, of all things. &nbsp;It's very long and full of Latin legal terms and I can't say I bother to read the whole thing. &nbsp;After I sign, I feel an itching behind my eye. &nbsp;I start rubbing it and something small and shining and round falls out. &nbsp;Before I can see what it is, the salesman snatches it and puts it into a drawer beneath the counter.<br /><br />I start to ask him about it, but before I can he says, "Which opera is sir going to see tonight?"<br /><br />"To be honest, I don't know. &nbsp;My girlfriend picked it. &nbsp;Something by Berlitz? &nbsp;Belize?"<br /><br />"Ah, yes. &nbsp;Berlioz. &nbsp;'The Damnation of Faust'. &nbsp;A particular favourite of mine, sir. &nbsp;I trust you'll enjoy it. &nbsp;Have a wonderful evening. &nbsp;I do so look forward to seeing you again."<br /><br />I turn and find my way through the maze of the shop, back up the stairs to chilly London.<br /><br /></div>


<h2>Comments</h2>


<div class='comments'>
<div class='comment'>
<div class='author'>Jonathan Lange<span class='comment-date'> on 2013-02-15 14:11</span></div>
<div class='content'>
Thanks! You&#39;re right about the 2nd para. I can only plead deadlines.</div>
</div>
<div class='comment'>
<div class='author'>JB<span class='comment-date'> on 2013-02-14 22:35</span></div>
<div class='content'>
I adore the language you&#39;ve used here Jonathan, well done. Perhaps consider rewording the second sentence of paragraph two. Your use of the time period &#39;last week&#39; twice in the same sentence detracts from an otherwise absorbing read. Or, perhaps it was just my OCD tendencies that drew me out of the story when I read that particular line.</div>
</div>
<div class='comment'>
<div class='author'>Jonathan Lange<span class='comment-date'> on 2013-02-01 10:19</span></div>
<div class='content'>
Hey Al,<br /><br />So glad you liked it!<br /><br />Also, I&#39;ve sat here puzzling for a good few minutes and can&#39;t place the earring reference. Where&#39;s it from?<br /><br />jml</div>
</div>
<div class='comment'>
<div class='author'>SuperMatty<span class='comment-date'> on 2013-02-01 00:27</span></div>
<div class='content'>
I don&#39;t think Wodehouse will be too perturbed :)<br /><br />PS: please please *please* don&#39;t slip over in the street while inhabiting your suit. Perhaps you need a cane as well...</div>
</div>
<div class='comment'>
<div class='author'>Alistair Campbell<span class='comment-date'> on 2013-01-31 22:53</span></div>
<div class='content'>
:)<br />Reading this made my morning, jml!<br />Wonderful imagery and warm, engaging language.<br />Loved it!<br />(although I was hoping that you&#39;d offer (in a Scottish accent) to pay for your suit of clothes with an ancient pearl earring removed directly from your earlobe!)</div>
</div>
<div class='comment'>
<div class='author'>Jason<span class='comment-date'> on 2013-01-31 00:05</span></div>
<div class='content'>
Jonathan, you make me want to burn my keyboard with alarming regularity.</div>
</div>
<div class='comment'>
<div class='author'>Jonathan Lange<span class='comment-date'> on 2013-01-20 17:49</span></div>
<div class='content'>
With apologies to Gene Wolfe &amp; P. G. Wodehouse.</div>
</div>
</div>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
