<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

	<title><![CDATA[Echo and Bounce]]></title>
	<link href="http://life.mumak.net/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
	<link href="http://life.mumak.net/"/>
	<updated>2013-09-22T15:38:10+01:00</updated>
	<id>http://life.mumak.net/</id>
	<author>
		<name><![CDATA[Jonathan Lange]]></name>
		
	</author>
	<generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

	
	<entry>
		
			<title type="html"><![CDATA[Shelter]]></title>
		
		<link href="http://life.mumak.net/2013/09/shelter.html"/>
		<updated>2013-09-22T14:17:00+01:00</updated>
		<id>http://life.mumak.net/2013/09/shelter</id>
		<content type="html">
			<![CDATA[
				
					<p></p>
				
			]]>
			<![CDATA[<p>We don&rsquo;t have to read
<a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/A_Canticle_for_Leibowitz"><em>A Canticle for Leibowitz</em></a>
for long before we get to the fallout shelter.</p>

<hr />

<p><strong>Warning:</strong> spoilers follow.  <em>A Canticle for Leibowitz</em> is a great book, and
it would be a great pity if you were to read this little essay without reading
the book first.  I can&rsquo;t get
<a href="http://octopress.org/docs/blogging/plugins/">Octopress&rsquo;s excerpt feature</a> to
work yet, so here&rsquo;s the warning again:</p>

<p><strong>Spoilers follow.  Stop reading now.</strong></p>

<hr />

<!--more-->


<p>When we get there, we discover the remnants of a civilization that managed to
incinerate itself despite all of its wealth, power, and knowledge.  All that
remains within the crumbling concrete structure are bones and a few scraps of
paper.</p>

<p>It would not be fair to say that <em>Canticle</em> is primarily about the question of
where we can find safety &mdash; if anything, it is about the two-edged nature of
knowledge &mdash; but places of refuge are a theme throughout the book, and their
problems mirror the problems of the human condition.</p>

<p>The fallout shelter itself is long, long disused.  When Brother Francis finds
it, he marvels at its engineering and is boggled by its terminology, thinking
perhaps that a fallout is a kind of salamander.  And yet, for all of its
technological wonder, he finds in it the bones of its occupants.  As everyone
who lives after the &ldquo;flame deluge&rdquo; knows, knowledge is not enough to spare one
from destruction.</p>

<p>And yet, Brother Francis belongs to an order of monks dedicated to preserving
the knowledge of the past.  Their abbey guards sacred, original texts – the
Memorabilia – protecting it both from the ravages of time and from an angry
populace that has come to resent all book-learning.</p>

<p>Protecting it also from kings.  Much as in
<a href="http://hpmor.org">Harry Potter and the Methods of Rationality</a>, the monks
come to believe that scientific knowledge will inevitably be abused by those
with political power.  Thus they are divided, for although they begin by
sheltering this knowledge from a hurt and angry world, they must eventualy do
their best from allowing a greedy, gluttonous world to devour it, and consume
it for its own violent purposes.</p>

<p>Thus, that which shelters also imprisons.  That which makes the abbey a place
of safety for scholars, monks, and ancient texts also makes it an ideal
military outpost.</p>

<p>Even the spiritual safety of the Church is questioned.  Yes, there is much
wisdom there, and a long, long historical perspective that scientists and
politicians seem to lack.  But there is also bickering and infighting, spying
and political intrigue, cowardice and lying.</p>

<p>At one point, <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Walter_M._Miller,_Jr.">Miller</a>
refers to a line from G. K. Chesterton.  When asked &ldquo;what is wrong with the
world?&rdquo;, Chesterton replied, &ldquo;I am&rdquo;.  Whether in a monastery or a university
or a parliament or a hermit&rsquo;s hut, we can find no true shelter, for we always
bring the storm within ourselves.</p>

<p>The final parts of the book pit the ultimate forms of shelter against each
other.  On one side, a doctor contends for the merciful sleep of death, where
one is surely safe from the very real suffering in this life.  On the other
side, a priest offers the hope of salvation.  Where should one seek refuge?
In <em>Canticle</em>, Miller raises the question, and leaves us to find our own
answer.</p>
]]>
		</content>
	</entry>
	
	<entry>
		
			<title type="html"><![CDATA[Serve]]></title>
		
		<link href="http://life.mumak.net/2013/09/serve.html"/>
		<updated>2013-09-15T10:59:00+01:00</updated>
		<id>http://life.mumak.net/2013/09/serve</id>
		<content type="html">
			<![CDATA[
				
					<p></p>
				
			]]>
			<![CDATA[<p>I&rsquo;m hijacking this week&rsquo;s carefully chosen word to talk about changes to the
way I&rsquo;m serving my blogs, but before I get there, have some random musings.</p>

<p>It&rsquo;s a funny old word, &lsquo;serve&rsquo;.  We use it to talk about another computer, a
server, that does things for your computer, a client.</p>

<p>When we use &ldquo;serve&rdquo; of people, we almost always have a hierarchy in mind.  The
one who serves is lower than the one being served.</p>

<p>And yet, sometimes we grant people the title &ldquo;servant&rdquo; in order to do them
honour.  Thus the most powerful person in Britian is the &ldquo;first servant&rdquo;, or
Prime Minister.  This is perhaps due to a
<a href="http://www.biblegateway.com/passage/?search=Mark%2010:42-45&amp;version=NIV">Christian legacy</a>.</p>

<p>Certainly with computers on the web, it&rsquo;s this way.  Servers act only on the
initiative of their client, and well run services put the needs of their
clients well ahead of their own.  It&rsquo;s far from a perfect metaphor, since
well-behaved clients do exactly what they are told.</p>

<p>Curiously, the metaphor of the hierarchy is inverted.  While a human servant
is considered below a human master, a computer client invariably downloads
from its server, or pushes <em>up</em> to its server, thus placing the server above
the client.</p>

<!-- more -->


<h2>What&rsquo;s happened?</h2>

<p>I&rsquo;ve moved this blog and <a href="http://code.mumak.net">my technical blog</a> over to
<a href="http://octopress.org">Octopress</a>, which is a very geeky way of blogging that
allows me to write blog posts using the tools I use to write code.</p>

<h2>Why the change?</h2>

<h3>More fun while writing</h3>

<p>Blogger is nice for what it is, but it&rsquo;s actually a hassle to use for
composition.  It doesn&rsquo;t have rich styles for formatting, doesn&rsquo;t allow
footnotes, and has very poor support for managing literal line breaks, which
is critically important when you are writing about source code.</p>

<p>It has great, built-in support for analysing the traffic that comes to the
site, but that&rsquo;s not something that&rsquo;s very useful to me.  It turns out, gentle
reader, that you are one of a very select group.</p>

<p>My hope is that by serving my blogs with fresher technologies that I actually
enjoy using, and by lowering the barrier to publication, I&rsquo;ll have something
that is more interesting to me and perhaps more interesting to others.</p>

<h3>Clearer online presence</h3>

<p>I&rsquo;m not at all happy with <a href="http://mumak.net">mumak.net</a>.  I want it to be
focused on my technical and open source interests and to incorporate my
technical blog, currently served from <a href="http://code.mumak.net">code.mumak.net</a>.</p>

<p>The <a href="http://life.mumak.net">life.mumak.net</a> blog and related content would
then move to my halfwise domains, which aren&rsquo;t anywhere near as established.</p>

<p>The hope is that this will let me do a better job with both.</p>

<h3>Ramping up technical presence</h3>

<p>The
<a href="http://life.mumak.net/2013/01/the-alphabet-supremacy.html">Alphabet Supremacy</a>
project has meant that almost all of my writing time has been devoted to
non-technical things.  It&rsquo;s fun, but my appetite for open source hacking and
for technical writing has been whetted by stimulating conversations at
<a href="http://www.google.com/about/jobs/">work</a> and (perversely but predictably) by
being compelled to write about other things.</p>

<p>I&rsquo;ve been using <a href="https://thoughtstreams.io/jml/">ThoughtStreams</a> to help get
some of that stuff drafted.  The switch in technologies will make moving that
to my own domains easier.</p>

<h2>Technical details</h2>

<p>I tried <a href="http://ruhoh.com/">ruhoh</a> initially, but found it to be rather
complicated, and struggled to find themes that I didn&rsquo;t hate.  Some folk
talked about <a href="http://liquidluck.readthedocs.org/en/latest/">liquidluck</a>, which
I would like because it&rsquo;s written in Python and thus more hackable by me, but
after some initial struggles I decided to go with something a little more
popular.</p>

<p>Thus, <a href="http://octopress.org">octopress</a> was the next port of call and so far
seems to have worked out OK.  Perhaps I&rsquo;ll experiment with moving to
<a href="http://jekyllrb.com/">Jekyll</a> or try liquidluck again.  Now that I&rsquo;m off
blogger and have all of my data in relatively parseable formats, it&rsquo;s much
easier to experiment.</p>

<p>The new blog pages are being served by <a href="http://www.heroku.com/">Heroku</a>, in a
manner which I do not yet understand.  I picked it because it&rsquo;s free, because
there were
<a href="http://octopress.org/docs/deploying/heroku/">instructions in the octopress documentation</a>,
because I already have github pages and didn&rsquo;t want to bother figuring out
have to have three different site, ad I <em>really</em> don&rsquo;t want to host things
myself anymore.</p>

<h2>What happened to the comments?</h2>

<p>All of the existing comments are still on the site, but new comments are
disabled for now, and possibly forever.  If you think I should put them back
on, please feel free to make your case on the social network of your choice.</p>

<p>Anyway, please let me know if your blog reading experience is disrupted in any
way.  I&rsquo;ve tried hard to keep all of the old links still working, but it&rsquo;s
really easy to make mistakes.</p>
]]>
		</content>
	</entry>
	
	<entry>
		
			<title type="html"><![CDATA[Rat]]></title>
		
		<link href="http://life.mumak.net/2013/09/rat.html"/>
		<updated>2013-09-08T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
		<id>http://life.mumak.net/2013/09/rat</id>
		<content type="html">
			<![CDATA[
				
					<p></p>
				
			]]>
			<![CDATA[<div class='post'>
The most visceral memory I have of our trip to New York a couple of weeks ago was on a walk Jolie &amp; I took along the Hudson River.<br /><br />Jolie&#8217;s friends recommended a bunch of places for us to go see. We were just coming from one of them, a downtown pizza joint that we were slowly waddling away from, leaving behind a confused server and two-thirds of the one and only pizza we ordered. Never order a pizza in America unless there are at least five people around who are willing to give you a hand.<br /><br />Anyway, we&#8217;re walking down the Hudson, hand-in-hand in the moonlight on our way to a bar that runs in a converted ship, when our path is crossed by this huge rat, just sitting there on the footpath underneath the lights. He didn&#8217;t look like he was doing much, just chilling out on the river, enjoying the breeze.<br /><br />I actually don&#8217;t know if he was huge as rats go, since that&#8217;s the only one I&#8217;ve seen. At first, I thought it was a slightly bulky chihuahua. When we figured out what it was, I was a bit surprised it wasn&#8217;t busy inducting its turtle friends in the mysteries of ninjitsu. If I&#8217;d known, I would have brought them pizza.<br /><br />All the while, it&#8217;s just sitting there, bold as brass and in no mind to move off the footpath. I hadn&#8217;t been in New York long enough to insist on my right of way, so I navigated us gently around Master Splinter and resumed our night-time amble toward wobbly-decked drinks, glancing over my shoulder very occasionally – only every three seconds or so – to make sure that no rodent horde was pursuing us.<br /><br />I went to New York with a bit of a preconception that the natives were a bit rude, always in a hurry and more than willing to let you know about it. I didn&#8217;t find it that way. The dog-sized rat there was easily the rudest New Yorker we met, and he was surprisingly relaxed for a repellent pest that&#8217;s loathed by all and sundry. I guess he knew there were plenty worse places to be than in Manhattan in the moonlight.<br /><br /><span style="font-size: x-small;">This post is part of the <a href="http://life.mumak.net/2013/01/the-alphabet-supremacy.html">Alphabet Supremacy</a>, a collaboration with <a href="http://life.metagnome.net/">Bice Dibley</a>. Next week&#8217;s word is &#8220;serve&#8221;.</span></div>
]]>
		</content>
	</entry>
	
	<entry>
		
			<title type="html"><![CDATA[Real]]></title>
		
		<link href="http://life.mumak.net/2013/09/real.html"/>
		<updated>2013-09-01T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
		<id>http://life.mumak.net/2013/09/real</id>
		<content type="html">
			<![CDATA[
				
					<p></p>
				
			]]>
			<![CDATA[<div class='post'>
&#8220;Yes, but things are different in the real world.&#8221;<br /><br />It&#8217;s perhaps not <i>the </i>most patronizing thing you can say to someone, but it&#8217;s close to being the most patronizing thing anyone has said to me. (And I am deeply aware, gentle reader, that it is a privilege for me to be able to say so).<br /><br />When I was at school, I was told the real world was and would be different. After I got online, people reminded me that I needed to spend time in the real world. When I went to university, graduates in full-time employment assumed an air of superior knowledge and sagely informed me that the real world was a different place. When I started work and my colleagues found out I was into open source software, they were happy to tell me how that sort of thing just doesn&#8217;t work in the real world. When later I started work at Canonical, more than one person would patiently explain to me that sooner or later the pressures of the real world would cause the company to collapse. Now, at Google, I occasionally hear people joke about how it&#8217;s scary out there in the real world since you have to pay for your food out there.<br /><br />There is exactly one real world. It is the world that we are all living, breathing, eating and sleeping in. We have never in our lives left the real world. Each and every day has been spent within its confines, and it will be so every day until we go to our graves. If it turns out that there is life after that, then that too will be as real as today.<br /><br />Is it possible that the very fabric of the universe shifts and alters at the gates of academia? That friends in the schoolyard mean less than friends in the workplace? Is it really true that being a jerk to someone online is somehow less real than being a jerk to someone standing next to you? Perhaps the laws of physics are suspended at Google, allowing the chefs to conjure food from the ether.<br /><br />No. It&#8217;s very clear what people actually mean when they say &#8220;the real world&#8221;. They mean &#8220;my world&#8221;, and add to it the sheer effrontery of suggesting that only their experience and the experience of those like them has any validity whatsoever.<br /><br />To tell someone that things are different in the real world is to deny them an authentic experience of reality. That which you have lived through is of less value than that which I have lived through. My concerns have weight, yours are ephemeral. My achievements are solid, yours are imagined. I have the boldness to face the truth and all of its harsh consequences, while you wrap yourself in the warm blanket of pleasant delusion. I matter, you do not.<br /><br />I won&#8217;t bear any grudge if you use the phrase to compare and contrast obviously imagined worlds to reality. For example, &#8220;in Tolkien&#8217;s Middle Earth, the Silmarils and later the Rings of Power are central, and the lives of thousands turn on them. In the real world, jewellery is rarely that important&#8221;. If you said that, we might go on to have a spirited discussion about the diamond industry, but I wouldn&#8217;t object to your phrasing.<br /><br />However, if you say something daft like &#8220;Well, all of this open source software is well and good but in the real world we have to think about money&#8221;, then I&#8217;m afraid it&#8217;s going to be difficult for us to converse further.<br /><br /><span style="background-color: white; color: #333333; font-family: Helvetica; font-size: 13px; text-align: justify;">This post is part of the&nbsp;</span><a href="http://life.mumak.net/2013/01/the-alphabet-supremacy.html" style="-webkit-transition: color 0.3s; background-color: white; color: #009eb8; display: inline; font-family: 'Helvetica Neue Light', HelveticaNeue-Light, 'Helvetica Neue', Helvetica, Arial, sans-serif; font-size: 13px; outline: none; text-align: justify; text-decoration: none; transition: color 0.3s;">Alphabet Supremacy</a><span style="background-color: white; color: #333333; font-family: Helvetica; font-size: 13px; text-align: justify;">&nbsp;project, a collaboration between myself and&nbsp;</span><a href="http://life.metagnome.net/" style="-webkit-transition: color 0.3s; background-color: white; color: #009eb8; display: inline; font-family: 'Helvetica Neue Light', HelveticaNeue-Light, 'Helvetica Neue', Helvetica, Arial, sans-serif; font-size: 13px; outline: none; text-align: justify; text-decoration: none; transition: color 0.3s;">Bice Dibley</a><span style="background-color: white; color: #333333; font-family: Helvetica; font-size: 13px; text-align: justify;">. He chooses next week&#8217;s word.</span></div>
]]>
		</content>
	</entry>
	
	<entry>
		
			<title type="html"><![CDATA[Quick]]></title>
		
		<link href="http://life.mumak.net/2013/08/quick.html"/>
		<updated>2013-08-18T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
		<id>http://life.mumak.net/2013/08/quick</id>
		<content type="html">
			<![CDATA[
				
					<p></p>
				
			]]>
			<![CDATA[<div class='post'>
Sometimes I wonder how <i>The Flash</i>&nbsp;can stand it. Not only does he have to struggle through life wearing the world&#8217;s most ridiculous hat, but he must spend subjective aeons of time forced to watch the rest of us faff.<br /><br />Imagine you&#8217;re Barry Allen, aka <i>The Flash</i>, and you&#8217;ve got guests over for dinner. It&#8217;s time for coffee and you realize all of a sudden that you don&#8217;t have any milk. &#8220;No problem&#8221;, you think, &#8220;I&#8217;ll just nip out to the shops and get some&#8221;. After all, you sip from the well of the Speed Force, how long could it possibly take?<br /><br />But on the way down the stairs from your apartment, a large couple have decided to stop on the stair case and have an argument about whether or not they actually did buy bacon when they were out at the supermarket. Now, their conversation takes maybe only fifteen or twenty seconds, but if you can move and react a hundred-thousand times faster than a regular human, then that&#8217;s equivalent to almost a month.<br /><br />Now, I&#8217;m not suggesting that the Flash is stuck in a time stream that moves much, much slower than hours and that he is always watching us continentally drift through our lives. But even so, when he&#8217;s waiting in line at a supermarket, he <i>could </i>by doing something else. In fact, he could be doing, much, much more. For every instant in his stream of consciousness, he is presumably making a decision to not rush ahead and get all of everyone&#8217;s shopping scanned and packed in 7.42s so he can get back to fighting crime or watching Breaking Bad or whatever it is that he actually does. Even if he has some control over how he perceives the flow of time, the crucial thing is that he always <i>knows</i> that he could be going faster if only people would just hurry up a little.<br /><br />It turns out that I am not a patient man, and that I&#8217;m indulging myself by project myself onto DC&#8217;s fastest hero, albeit sans hat. I am all in favour of languorous leisure time, but I see no reason why one should dawdle when filling out forms, and can find no excuse for the person who has waited fifteen minutes in a bank queue only to arrive at the teller entirely unprepared for the experience. There is a time and a place to stop and smell the roses, and it is in a rose garden, not in your local branch of Lloyds TSB. When a dozen people behind you are on the last famished legs of their lunch break, more conscious than ever of their mortality, then one ought to push the tempo.<br /><br />But what an ugly way to live, to be always and ever mildly irked at all the poor souls who haven&#8217;t put as much time and energy into learning the fastest way to use a self-checkout as I have. I don&#8217;t even have to play the &#8220;well, they might have just come from the doctors with terrible news&#8221; game to see it&#8217;s wrong. While it&#8217;s true that you never know what&#8217;s going on in someone&#8217;s head, and that Fundamental Attribution Error is a real thing, and there is only one true judge, that still doesn&#8217;t help me, because that still leaves some people who are slow with no excuse and in my way.<br /><br />What I need to remember are the people who&#8217;ve patiently waited for me to figure things out after I&#8217;ve made the same mistake again &amp; again, the people who&#8217;ve waiting for me to (literally) stop standing on their feet, to (figuratively) stop making an ass of myself, to realize exactly what it was I just said, to say sorry, for me to be sorry.<br /><br /><span style="background-color: white; color: #333333; font-family: Helvetica; font-size: 13px; text-align: justify;">This post is part of the&nbsp;</span><a href="http://life.mumak.net/2013/01/the-alphabet-supremacy.html" style="-webkit-transition: color 0.3s; background-color: white; color: #009eb8; display: inline; font-family: 'Helvetica Neue Light', HelveticaNeue-Light, 'Helvetica Neue', Helvetica, Arial, sans-serif; font-size: 13px; outline: none; text-align: justify; text-decoration: none; transition: color 0.3s;">Alphabet Supremacy</a><span style="background-color: white; color: #333333; font-family: Helvetica; font-size: 13px; text-align: justify;">&nbsp;project, a collaboration between myself and&nbsp;</span><a href="http://life.metagnome.net/" style="-webkit-transition: color 0.3s; background-color: white; color: #009eb8; display: inline; font-family: 'Helvetica Neue Light', HelveticaNeue-Light, 'Helvetica Neue', Helvetica, Arial, sans-serif; font-size: 13px; outline: none; text-align: justify; text-decoration: none; transition: color 0.3s;">Bice Dibley</a><span style="background-color: white; color: #333333; font-family: Helvetica; font-size: 13px; text-align: justify;">. He chooses next week&#8217;s word.</span></div>
]]>
		</content>
	</entry>
	
	<entry>
		
			<title type="html"><![CDATA[Pasta]]></title>
		
		<link href="http://life.mumak.net/2013/08/pasta.html"/>
		<updated>2013-08-09T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
		<id>http://life.mumak.net/2013/08/pasta</id>
		<content type="html">
			<![CDATA[
				
					<p></p>
				
			]]>
			<![CDATA[<div class='post'>
There&#8217;s really no way to say this without offending some folk, so I&#8217;m going to go ahead and say it straight. Pasta is the Coldplay of the food world: bland, over-played filler squarely aimed at deluding the bourgeoisie into thinking they&#8217;ve got an creative edge.<br /><br />I&#8217;ll admit there are very rare circumstances, a bowl of freshly made pasta with a simple sauce can be a dish to nourish the soul as well as the body. Sadly, these circumstances almost never arrive, and instead we – the people – are forever saddled with squeaky, squishy, off-white starch, passing itself off as a meal. No food should have to pass itself as a bow-tie in order to be eaten.<br /><br />Macaroni &amp; cheese, you say? Jacket potato says I. Lasagne? Why not pizza. Your play is spaghetti bolognese, but I&#8217;ll counter with chicken tikka masala.<br /><br />I&#8217;m coming on strong to make a point. I don&#8217;t actually <i>hate</i>&nbsp;the stuff, and certainly won&#8217;t think less of you if you happen to like pasta. Or Coldplay, even. It&#8217;s just not my scene.<br /><br />Now, although the chances are undoubtedly slimmed after publishing this despicably graceless blog post, if you happen to invite me around for dinner at your place and we end up munching on tagliatelle and listening to <i>Parachutes</i>, I won&#8217;t utter a word of complaint and will eat up everything you deign to put on my plate. I&#8217;m a bigot, not a brute. I would be so gobsmacked with gratitude that mere details as to which starch – musical or nutritional – we choose to fill ourselves with will pale into insignificance.<br /><br />After all – and I am at least eighty percent serious about this – what&#8217;s the point of living if we can&#8217;t enjoy the company of our friends at the dinner table? Cold nights with warm, comforting food (I really don&#8217;t care if it&#8217;s pasta, potatoes, polenta, pumpkin or parsnips), enough wine to gently lift the heart and pleasant company to make it all worthwhile.<br /><br /><span style="font-size: 13px;">This post is part of the&nbsp;</span><a href="http://life.mumak.net/2013/01/the-alphabet-supremacy.html" style="font-size: 13px;">Alphabet Supremacy</a><span style="font-size: 13px;">&nbsp;project, a collaboration between myself and&nbsp;</span><a href="http://life.metagnome.net/" style="font-size: 13px;">Bice Dibley</a><span style="font-size: 13px;">. Next week&#8217;s word is &#8220;quick&#8221;.</span></div>
]]>
		</content>
	</entry>
	
	<entry>
		
			<title type="html"><![CDATA[Protect]]></title>
		
		<link href="http://life.mumak.net/2013/08/protect.html"/>
		<updated>2013-08-04T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
		<id>http://life.mumak.net/2013/08/protect</id>
		<content type="html">
			<![CDATA[
				
					<p></p>
				
			]]>
			<![CDATA[<div class='post'>
Last week, I mentioned that I&#8217;m on a roster at Christ Church Mayfair. &nbsp;This week, although &#8220;protect&#8221; too grandiose a word for it, I&#8217;d like to share a bit about what it is actually do, and why.<br /><br />Roughly speaking, my job is to keep people out of church, and to make sure that those in the service don&#8217;t disrupt it. &nbsp;If you think of the role as a bouncer, you wouldn&#8217;t be too far off.<br /><br />It&#8217;s not typical for churches to have a rota of bouncers. &nbsp;Generally speaking, we&#8217;d like as many people through the door as we can possibly get – we call it &#8220;good news&#8221; for a reason. &nbsp;Hosting an evening service in central London, however, means that we often get people who turn up who for one reason or another are best turned away.<br /><br />The most common and the most benign are tourists who want to look at the building. &nbsp;CCM is a traditional church building that was built by the Victorians and survived the blitz. &nbsp;It&#8217;s also the closest churchy looking building to a bunch of very expensive hotels. &nbsp;Plenty of tourists want to have a peek inside. &nbsp;If they want to join the service, they are most welcome, but if they just want to take snapshots of the ceiling, we&#8217;d rather they come back some other time.<br /><br />We also occasionally get people who are there with the express intent of disrupting the service, shouting and angry or shouting and mocking as the case may be. &nbsp;Occasionally they&#8217;re rich lads on a night out, but mostly this comes from rough sleepers with untreated mental illnesses. &nbsp;I really don&#8217;t know what do for those guys, except to be kind and patient and make sure they don&#8217;t come inside unless they calm down first.<br /><br />I have to stress, we don&#8217;t refuse people based on how they look, how rich or poor they are, whether they are on a list (there isn&#8217;t one) or whether they&#8217;ve been drinking. &nbsp;The basis of admission <i>while a service is running</i> is whether they&#8217;ll disrupt the service.<br /><br />The last and least pleasant thing that I&#8217;ve had to deal with is men being creeps to women. &nbsp;Once or twice we&#8217;ve had men corner women and make repeated, unwanted advances. &nbsp;At least one such man has freely confessed to using pick-up artist tactics to try to &#8220;trick&#8221; (his words) women into giving him their phone numbers.<br /><br />The last incident like that happened while I was on duty, and frankly, I didn&#8217;t know what to do. &nbsp;I tried once to talk to him but he gave me the brush off, so the rest of the evening I stuck to him like glue. &nbsp;Useless. &nbsp;His overall pattern of behaviour was clearly, obviously dodgy but there was no single action I could point to that I could confidently call out. &nbsp;How odd it is to feel bound by social norms while someone else dances on their edge. Should I say something? &nbsp;What should I say? &nbsp;Why isn&#8217;t she asking for help? Am I white-knighting? &nbsp;What if I tell him to stop and he says &#8216;stop what&#8217;? &nbsp;Is there something innocuous I can say to draw him into conversation? Next time – and sadly, there&#8217;ll probably be a next time – I&#8217;ll just be rude. It&#8217;ll probably be a mistake, but at least it&#8217;ll be a different one.<br /><br />And that&#8217;s pretty much it. &nbsp;I&#8217;ve focused on the difficult bits, mostly I just end up sitting in the vestibule all evening, opening the door for people as they come in.<br /><br />I should add that this is all very much my own take on things, and whatever resemblance it has to the official stance of Christ Church Mayfair is purely coincidental.<br /><div><br /></div></div>
]]>
		</content>
	</entry>
	
	<entry>
		
			<title type="html"><![CDATA[Occasion]]></title>
		
		<link href="http://life.mumak.net/2013/07/occasion.html"/>
		<updated>2013-07-28T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
		<id>http://life.mumak.net/2013/07/occasion</id>
		<content type="html">
			<![CDATA[
				
					<p></p>
				
			]]>
			<![CDATA[<div class='post'>
Phoning this one in, I&#8217;m afraid, since today has been that rarest of occasions: a Sunday almost entirely to myself.<br /><br />My normal Sunday consists of me getting up at around 9am and heading to St Johns church, picking up a coffee on the way. &nbsp;St Johns is an extremely casual church on a housing estate, embedded in some hideous brick skyscrapers. It nominally starts at 11am, but I&#8217;m on a roster often enough to need to be there by 10 or 10:30 a lot of weeks. &nbsp;Jolie&#8217;s always there before 10, grooving away on her bass.<br /><br />By the time the service is finished, and we&#8217;ve done chatting with everyone, it&#8217;s about 1:30pm and we start wandering home. When the weather is even a little bit nice, we walk, since it&#8217;s pleasant and mostly flat. I carry Jolie&#8217;s bass so people will think I&#8217;m cooler than I actually am.<br /><br />Then we get home, and I start bashing out my Alphabet Supremacy piece for the week, Jolie makes us lunch and when all that&#8217;s done we chill out until about 4:30 - 5pm when we leave for the things we&#8217;re rostered on for at Christ Church Mayfair. We don&#8217;t get back from there until around 9:30pm.<br /><br />I do all of that because it&#8217;s important to me. But sometimes, it&#8217;s nice to have a solid chunk of time when I just get things done.<br /><br />Today has provided such an opportunity, as I&#8217;ve been obliged to spend the day at home. It&#8217;s been wonderful. I&#8217;ve been able to do so many dull but essential things like laundry, budgeting (you&#8217;d think that lists of numbers that add up to zero would be less work), a little bit of writing, and a lot of todos that will make the week run smoother for having done them (wedding invitations don&#8217;t become calendar appointments by themselves!).<br /><br />I&#8217;ve also had a chance to listen to Das Rheingold for the first time. &nbsp;It&#8217;s really good, and I&#8217;m looking forward to listening to it again and perhaps even <i>watching</i>&nbsp;it, so I can figure out who is singing what.<br /><br />Now the geas which kept me housebound has broken and I&#8217;m off to CCM. Plans won&#8217;t get me back in time to write something more suitable, so you&#8217;ll have to look to Mr Dibley to supply the quality for the week.<br /><br /><span style="background-color: white; font-family: Helvetica; font-size: 13px;">This post is part of the&nbsp;</span><a href="http://life.mumak.net/2013/01/the-alphabet-supremacy.html" style="background-color: white; font-size: 13px;">Alphabet Supremacy</a><span style="background-color: white; font-family: Helvetica; font-size: 13px;">&nbsp;project, a collaboration between myself and&nbsp;</span><a href="http://life.metagnome.net/" style="background-color: white; font-size: 13px;">Bice Dibley</a><span style="background-color: white; font-family: Helvetica; font-size: 13px;">. Next week&#8217;s word is <i>protect</i>.</span></div>
]]>
		</content>
	</entry>
	
	<entry>
		
			<title type="html"><![CDATA[Office]]></title>
		
		<link href="http://life.mumak.net/2013/07/office.html"/>
		<updated>2013-07-21T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
		<id>http://life.mumak.net/2013/07/office</id>
		<content type="html">
			<![CDATA[
				
					<p></p>
				
			]]>
			<![CDATA[<div class='post'>
The day starts with the sound of the ocean gently, steadily and, alas, digitally getting louder and louder until I can do the sums required to turn it off. &nbsp;It&#8217;s followed by a lot of hot water, a few cuts to the face, a walk past a church cum Indian cultural centre cum Ingress portal before I take a short ride getting way too familiar with the sights and scents of commuters&#8217; armpits. &nbsp;If I took the slightly longer route, I&#8217;d walk past the place Gandhi lived when he was a law student, but I won&#8217;t because it&#8217;s hot and I&#8217;m carrying fifteen pounds of kickboxing gear on my back.<br /><br />Victoria Station is vast and frenetic. &nbsp;Everyone is in the way. &nbsp;It is impossible to not be stressed here. &nbsp;Well, maybe Gandhi could have managed it. I&#8217;m hungry and everything smells of bakery. &nbsp;I don&#8217;t eat much bread these days, but that doesn&#8217;t mean I don&#8217;t want to leap the counter and forcefully grab a half-dozen croissants. &nbsp;The Japanese couple struggling up the stairs with suitcases twice as large as themselves misinterpret my snarl. &nbsp;I really should offer to help, but the moment passes.<br /><br />I shuffle slowly through the Tallest Glass Revolving Doors in Europe, fishing in my pocket for my ID to show to building security. &nbsp;Every time I see any security guards or bouncers these days, I wonder what it would be like to fight them. &nbsp;There&#8217;s one guy here who I reckon would be vicious. &nbsp;He&#8217;s small and looks maybe forty-five or fifty, but he&#8217;s always weirdly alert. &nbsp;When I say &#8220;Good morning&#8221;, he seems to regard it as a distraction from his watch.<br /><br />Once I&#8217;m through, I get to my floor. &nbsp;By now it&#8217;s familiar to me, but I still take the time to appreciate it. &nbsp;The corridors aren&#8217;t just soulless tunnels, but rich, interesting places with colour and texture. &nbsp;The deli &amp; micro-kitchens are cosy and relaxed. &nbsp;My desk maybe technically possibly counts as a cubical, but hasn&#8217;t ever felt that way to me.<br /><br />The first thing I do is get coffee, which Shakespeare would have called the chief nourisher in life&#8217;s feast if he only knew what he was on about. &nbsp;The coffee from the push-button machine isn&#8217;t great, but it works enough to get me ready to use the espresso machine for my sophomore cup.<br /><br />I worked from home for about eight years, in one way or another, and mostly enjoyed it. &nbsp;Now I&#8217;m here, I don&#8217;t miss it at all. &nbsp;Well, sometimes it&#8217;s a bit noisy, but there&#8217;s a beautiful, dark, quiet room where I can escape. &nbsp;The food is better, my computer is better, and the company is better.<br /><br />That is, one of the things I enjoy most about my trade is sitting around with a team, working together on something interesting. &nbsp;At my previous job, even though we worked from home mostly, we&#8217;d occasionally get together in some random city, sit in a room and hack on something for a solid week. &nbsp;Those weeks (NB:&nbsp;<i>not</i>&nbsp;the weeks where we sat around planning things) were the most fun times in a job that was overall a pretty fun job. &nbsp;So why not do that all the time?<br /><br />The day starts to wind up, I slug my kickboxing bag over my shoulder and head out. &nbsp;There&#8217;s a different, friendlier security guard on duty, but I only really see his back and I think we&#8217;d both be uncomfortable if I turned around and said &#8220;Good morning&#8221;. &nbsp;I get to Victoria Station, and though it shouldn&#8217;t be mathematically possible there are even more people here, and they all hate me for lugging this great bloody thing around, taking up precious standing room. As I&#8217;m shoved onto the train to Euston, I can&#8217;t help but think that I love this city.<br /><span style="background-color: white; font-family: Helvetica; font-size: 13px;"><br class="Apple-interchange-newline" />This post is part of the&nbsp;</span><a href="http://life.mumak.net/2013/01/the-alphabet-supremacy.html" style="background-color: white; font-size: 13px;">Alphabet Supremacy</a><span style="background-color: white; font-family: Helvetica; font-size: 13px;">&nbsp;project, a collaboration between myself and&nbsp;</span><a href="http://life.metagnome.net/" style="background-color: white; font-size: 13px;">Bice Dibley</a><span style="background-color: white; font-family: Helvetica; font-size: 13px;">. He chooses next week&#8217;s word.</span></div>
]]>
		</content>
	</entry>
	
	<entry>
		
			<title type="html"><![CDATA[Reading update 2013Q2]]></title>
		
		<link href="http://life.mumak.net/2013/07/reading-update-2013q2.html"/>
		<updated>2013-07-16T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
		<id>http://life.mumak.net/2013/07/reading-update-2013q2</id>
		<content type="html">
			<![CDATA[
				
					<p></p>
				
			]]>
			<![CDATA[<div class='post'>
Even more books this time.<br /><ul><li><i>Astonishing X-Men: Unstoppable</i>, Joss Whedon and John Cassaday&nbsp;</li><li><i>Batman: Year One</i>, Frank Miller and David Mazzucchelli</li><li><i>Flashpoint</i>, Geoff Johns and Andy Kubert</li><li><i>Saga, Volume 1</i>, Brian K. Vaughan and Fiona Staples</li><li><i>Getting More</i>, Stuart Diamond</li><li><i>Starting Strength</i>, Mark Rippetoe</li><li><i>ReWork</i>, Jason Fried and David Heinemeier Hansson</li><li><i>The Heroes</i>, Joe Abercrombie</li><li><i>Man&#8217;s Search for Meaning</i>, Victor Frankl</li><li><i>The Iron King</i>, Maurice Druon</li><li><i>The Moonstone</i>, Wilkie Collins</li><li><i>Persian Fire</i>, Tom Holland</li><li><i>The Design of Design</i>, Frederick P. Brooks</li><li><i>Home Fires</i>, Gene Wolfe</li><li><i>The Rest is Noise,</i>&nbsp;Alex Ross</li><li><i>Throne of the Crescent Moon</i>, Saladin Ahmed</li><li><i>The Datacenter as Computer</i>,&nbsp;Luiz André Barroso, Urs Hölzle</li><li><i>The Turn of the Screw and The Aspern Papers</i>, Henry James</li><li><i>Blood of Dragons</i>, Robin Hobb</li><li><i>Red Seas Under Red Skies</i>, Scott Lynch</li><li><i>The Lies of Locke Lamora</i>, Scott Lynch</li><li><i>Stories</i>, Neil Gaiman and Al Sarrantonio (editors)</li></ul></div>
]]>
		</content>
	</entry>
	
	<entry>
		
			<title type="html"><![CDATA[Negotiation]]></title>
		
		<link href="http://life.mumak.net/2013/07/negotiation.html"/>
		<updated>2013-07-07T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
		<id>http://life.mumak.net/2013/07/negotiation</id>
		<content type="html">
			<![CDATA[
				
					<p></p>
				
			]]>
			<![CDATA[<div class='post'>
I&#8217;m ashamed to say it, but we got absolutely spanked by the real estate agent who let us the flat where we&#8217;re now living. &nbsp;He talked us into higher rent, a longer lease and dropping the six month break clause. &nbsp;During the process of leasing it, he would hurry us up one day and stall us the next. &nbsp;He&#8217;d even tell us dubious half-truths about the place and the landlord. &nbsp;We like the place enough, and might even renew the release, but I don&#8217;t want to repeat that experience. &nbsp;Coming out with slightly less money and freedom is bad enough, but the process itself is slimy and humiliating.<br /><br />It&#8217;s not as if that was the first time I&#8217;ve walked away from a negotiation feeling like a sucker. &nbsp;Almost all of my previous tenancies and certain salary negotiations stand out as being terribly handled on my part.<br /><br />I&#8217;ve always felt it&#8217;s slightly unfair that two of the most important factors in my material happiness – how much I earn and where I live – are so strongly determined by something I&#8217;m just not very good at. &nbsp;In the Benign and Enlightened Suzerainty of Jonathania, your compensation and residence would be a function of your skill in some core, valuable profession, such as computer programming.<br /><br />Since, alas, the world is not yet my demesne, I&#8217;ve been trying to level up in negotiation. &nbsp;For a long time, the most helpful thing I read was Valerie Aurora&#8217;s <a href="http://valerieaurora.org/howto_salary/">HOWTO on salary negotiation</a>, written for women, but useful enough for me. &nbsp;It helped me grok what I mentioned above, that I shouldn&#8217;t use being a geek as an excuse for being naïve.<br /><br />Then I picked up the <a href="http://www.amazon.co.uk/The-Economist-Negotiation-Guide--Z/dp/1846681693/">Economist A-Z on negotiation</a>. &nbsp;It&#8217;s a really fun little read, and the ideal Father/Mother&#8217;s day present for the middle-class classical liberal in your life who already has everything. &nbsp;The highlights are the articles on &#8220;zero sum&#8221; (negotiation isn&#8217;t, which is why we haven&#8217;t had the merchant caste hanged already) and &#8220;children&#8221; (who play dirty and are thus the best negotiators, but get their comeuppance during courtship).<br /><br />But the most interesting and most recent book I&#8217;ve read on negotiation is Stuart Diamond&#8217;s &#8220;Getting More&#8221;. &nbsp;In it, Diamond asks us to stop thinking in terms of tactics and negotiating positions and to instead be crystal clear on our goals, understand where the other person is coming from and then help them meet our goals, mostly by framing your goals in a way that makes it easy for them to meet, by trading things of unequal value, and by holding them to their own standards.<br /><br />The book is crammed with anecdotes. &nbsp;No matter how small a slice of this book you take, you will find a positive, upbeat story about how one of his students used these principles to &#8220;get more&#8221;. &nbsp;If you had to drink a shot every time you came across one, they&#8217;d be wheeling in the stomach pump halfway through page two. &nbsp;By the end, you&#8217;ve been pummelled with so many that you&#8217;ve forgotten what the book is about.<br /><br />The underlying principles do seem sound, and when I&#8217;ve spoken with people who&#8217;ve read &#8220;Crucial Confrontations&#8221;, they say it very much matches the ideas in that book. &nbsp;I just wish that Diamond had put in more bullet point summaries or something to make the book seem more structured and less meandering.<br /><br />The closest he gets to an actual schema is in his &#8220;Planning&#8221; section, which has something close to a diagram, but is really just a few lists arranged in a grid. &nbsp;I wish he flagged that and said &#8220;this is it, this is the first and last chance you&#8217;ll have to see everything on one page&#8221;.<br /><br />There are a few times where his suggestions seem a touch unsavoury. &nbsp;When he talks about trading things of unequal value, he suggests &#8220;make emotional payments&#8221;, which is a fancy way of saying that you should strive to be kind and well-mannered. &nbsp;And if there&#8217;s a thing that I would be happy to buy for £100 and I negotiate the purchase for £80, then how exactly is that different from tricking the seller out of £20?<br /><br />Sadly, that&#8217;s all rather hypothetical. &nbsp;The one or two times I&#8217;ve tried to apply the ideas in the book, I&#8217;ve ended up happily and politely doing what I&#8217;m told.<br /><br />I just hope that the next real estate agent I deal with throws in a lollipop.<br /><div><br /></div><div><span style="background-color: white; font-family: Helvetica; font-size: 13px;">This post is part of the&nbsp;</span><a href="http://life.mumak.net/2013/01/the-alphabet-supremacy.html" style="background-color: white; font-size: 13px;">Alphabet Supremacy</a><span style="background-color: white; font-family: Helvetica; font-size: 13px;">&nbsp;project, a collaboration between myself and&nbsp;</span><a href="http://life.metagnome.net/" style="background-color: white; font-size: 13px;">Bice Dibley</a><span style="background-color: white; font-family: Helvetica; font-size: 13px;">. He chooses next week&#8217;s word.</span></div></div>
<h2>Comments</h2>
<div class='comments'>
<div class='comment'>
<div class='author'>Bron<span class='comment-date'> on 2013-07-09 13:21</span></div>
<div class='content'>
I feel your pain! Oh man, I really suck at this too. It just goes so against the grain for me. I have wondered if it&#39;s an introvert thing. I actually find it a lot easier to do over the phone or in writing. </div>
</div>
</div>
]]>
		</content>
	</entry>
	
	<entry>
		
			<title type="html"><![CDATA[Middle (reflections on the Alphabet Supremacy)]]></title>
		
		<link href="http://life.mumak.net/2013/06/middle-reflections-on-alphabet-supremacy.html"/>
		<updated>2013-06-30T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
		<id>http://life.mumak.net/2013/06/middle-reflections-on-alphabet-supremacy</id>
		<content type="html">
			<![CDATA[
				
					<p></p>
				
			]]>
			<![CDATA[<div class='post'>
Bice and I agreed that for this post we&#8217;d discuss our thoughts and reflections on the Alphabet Supremacy project so far. &nbsp;Here&#8217;s mine, which mostly date from about the end of March.<br /><h3>Writing process</h3><ul><li>Knowing that I&#8217;m going to write something every week means that I&#8217;m somewhat okay with writing and publishing something that I&#8217;m not happy with. &nbsp;Part of the exercise is acquiring the discipline of getting something out.</li><li>Also, I&#8217;m treating the whole thing as exercise rather than performance. That is, I&#8217;m using it as an excuse to try things, or to get better at things that I&#8217;ve struggled with.</li><li>This makes me particularly grateful to readers who actually continue to read. Thank you.</li><li>Although it&#8217;s not part of the rules, I&#8217;m avoiding using the bullet-point style that I prefer. That&#8217;s particularly because I want to exercise writing long form prose that&#8217;s coherent.</li><li>As I work on something, I very much wish that I could work on it more.</li><li>In particular, many, many ideas get discarded, some of which are better than the thing that gets published. &nbsp;Alas, time.</li><li>Also, I&#8217;m starting to learn to identify when I take the lazy way out in writing and also thinking. &nbsp;</li><li>I often want to write &#8220;Perhaps X&#8221; or &#8220;Maybe Y&#8221;, and when I do, it&#8217;s because I haven&#8217;t taken the time or made the effort to evaluate X or Y.</li><li>Sometimes I&#8217;ve had what I thought were interesting ideas, and then spent a lot of time developing them and then they turn out to be trite &amp; obvious. And then I delete them, and no one notices.</li><li>Composing an essay so that it has an actual&nbsp;<i>point</i>&nbsp;is rather hard.</li><li>Writing on a topic that&#8217;s chosen for me is a great way to get ideas for something,&nbsp;<i>anything</i>&nbsp;else to write. &nbsp;Making the time to develop those ideas is quite hard.</li><li>As a matter of principle, I think that most writers or speakers must first be entertainers. Perhaps some people are exceptions, but I don&#8217;t believe I&#8217;m one of them.&nbsp;</li><li>Why do we have principles? So we can constantly feel like failures and hypocrites.</li><li>Despite the fact that the whole reason I&#8217;m doing this is that I want to get better, I&#8217;m regularly surprised by just how hard it is to say what I mean.</li><li>I really want to be an essayist, but this far in, I think I prefer my fiction pieces more (in particular, <a href="http://life.mumak.net/2013/01/bargain.html">Bargain</a> and <a href="http://life.mumak.net/2013/05/indifference.html">Indifference</a>)</li></ul><h3>Interaction with Bice</h3><div><ul><li>Although it&#8217;s not a competition, I do make a bit of an internal decision about whether my post or Bice&#8217;s is the better one. &nbsp;I haven&#8217;t been keeping score though, which is most likely a sub-conscious reaction to having a lower score.</li><li>I don&#8217;t read Bice&#8217;s post until I&#8217;ve published mine. &nbsp;I accidentally did so once, and that made it very difficult for me to write mine.</li><li>We do sometimes talk about posts and our thinking process after we&#8217;ve written them. Most of this discussion has been logged, and it might be interesting to review &amp; perhaps publish it some time toward the end of the project.</li></ul><h3>Word Choice</h3></div><div><ul><li>Sometimes I choose words because they&#8217;ll be easy for me to write about. Sometimes because I want to see what Bice has to say. Other times because I want to be forced to write about something in particular.&nbsp;</li><li>At least once, I&#8217;ve chosen a word because I could see opportunities for both fiction and non-fiction pieces.</li><li>We don&#8217;t collude over the choice of words (except for this one!). &nbsp;We sometimes talk about it after the choice (e.g. I recently asked if &#8220;football&#8221; was deliberately chosen to make this week&#8217;s post difficult for me), but we don&#8217;t discuss what we&#8217;re planning to write.</li></ul></div><h3>Pragmatics</h3><ul><li>Writing a post takes between two and six hours of actually sitting at a laptop, writing and editing.</li><li>With my current schedule, that&#8217;s a significant but manageable amount of time. &nbsp;It mostly means I have to do less open source hacking, and do fewer spontaneous fun things on the weekend.</li><li>When I&#8217;m sick, or I have a busy weekend, or I&#8217;m travelling, it&#8217;s much harder to get something done.</li><li>Blogger isn&#8217;t a fun platform to compose on.</li><li>I&#8217;ve already missed multiple deadlines.</li><li>Jolie has been a huge help to me in getting these posts out. &nbsp;I can&#8217;t overstate this.</li><li>I would love the opportunity to spend a few months working a piece that I cared about. &nbsp;However, a few months of full time writing would probably drive me mad. &nbsp;And I&#8217;d almost certainly procrastinate until the last week anyway.</li></ul><span style="font-size: 13px;">This post is part of the&nbsp;</span><a href="http://life.mumak.net/2013/01/the-alphabet-supremacy.html" style="font-size: 13px;">Alphabet Supremacy</a><span style="font-size: 13px;">&nbsp;project, a collaboration between myself and&nbsp;</span><a href="http://life.metagnome.net/" style="font-size: 13px;">Bice Dibley</a><span style="font-size: 13px;">.</span></div>
<h2>Comments</h2>
<div class='comments'>
<div class='comment'>
<div class='author'>Jonathan Lange<span class='comment-date'> on 2013-07-01 16:22</span></div>
<div class='content'>
Ugh, no, sorry.  I wrote this before flying to the States and the word choice got lost in the timezone transition.<br /><br />Am struggling to think of anything to write about that I&#39;d actually find interesting.  How about &quot;negotiation&quot;.</div>
</div>
<div class='comment'>
<div class='author'>Bice Dibley<span class='comment-date'> on 2013-07-01 15:52</span></div>
<div class='content'>
Have you by cunning device implied next week&#39;s word is &quot;nothing&quot;?</div>
</div>
</div>
]]>
		</content>
	</entry>
	
	<entry>
		
			<title type="html"><![CDATA[Music]]></title>
		
		<link href="http://life.mumak.net/2013/06/music.html"/>
		<updated>2013-06-22T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
		<id>http://life.mumak.net/2013/06/music</id>
		<content type="html">
			<![CDATA[
				
					<p></p>
				
			]]>
			<![CDATA[<div class='post'>
When I was child, I never really thought of vanilla as a flavour. &nbsp;Chocolate, strawberry and triple swirl were all obviously real flavours, but vanilla wasn&#8217;t really. &nbsp;It didn&#8217;t even have a colour. &nbsp;It&#8217;s just the flavour of ice cream you use when you don&#8217;t want to be too distracted from the main event, as when eating apple pie.<br /><br />For a long time I used to think of the piano like a bit like vanilla ice cream. &nbsp;Sure it&#8217;s fine in its place, but it&#8217;s just the default instrument. I&#8217;m not sure why anyone would choose it over, say, chocolate&#8212;er, I mean, the cello.<br /><br />But one day I realized that vanilla was more than just the absence of flavour, and that it actually was a pretty good flavour, and how exactly was it to blame if it went so well with everything, and if you don&#8217;t mind I might just have some vanilla ice cream by itself thank you very much. &nbsp;Likewise, I&#8217;m starting to enjoy to listening to the piano for its own sake.<br /><br />Well, a little. &nbsp;One of my favourite pieces of music is Brahms&#8217; Cello Sonata in E Minor. &nbsp;During the last few listens my focus has moved away from the cello and toward the play between the cello and the piano. &nbsp;The dark, strong, forceful line of the cello is the espresso that is both cut and complemented by the (wait for it) vanilla ice cream of the piano. &nbsp;Molto affogato.<br /><br />I don&#8217;t know why I like that piece so much. &nbsp;I only picked it up because another piece on the disc is mentioned a lot in The Fionavar Tapestry and I wanted to know what it sounded like. I don&#8217;t like the books quite so much any more &#8211; pick your ice cream metaphor of choice &#8211; but I was entranced by them at the time, and perhaps that enchantment carried over, and when I listen to the sonatas on the album a part of me hears an echo of Pwyll and Loren and the rest.<br /><br />Meh. It&#8217;s just really good music.<br /><div><br /></div></div>
<h2>Comments</h2>
<div class='comments'>
<div class='comment'>
<div class='author'>Michael Hudson-Doyle<span class='comment-date'> on 2013-06-24 00:44</span></div>
<div class='content'>
After seeing an amazing live performance a few years back, I&#39;ve become a bit of a fan of Beethoven&#39;s piano sonatas, esp. no.23 &quot;appassionata&quot; </div>
</div>
</div>
]]>
		</content>
	</entry>
	
	<entry>
		
			<title type="html"><![CDATA[Laziness]]></title>
		
		<link href="http://life.mumak.net/2013/06/laziness.html"/>
		<updated>2013-06-16T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
		<id>http://life.mumak.net/2013/06/laziness</id>
		<content type="html">
			<![CDATA[
				
					<p></p>
				
			]]>
			<![CDATA[<div class='post'>
<br /><br />Seven ways I&#8217;m lazy.<br /><h3>Busyness as excuse</h3>I&#8217;ve been meaning to go to the gym to do some strength training. &nbsp;I&#8217;ve been thinking about it, planning for it, and talking about it for weeks, but I haven&#8217;t actually managed to go regularly. Why?<br /><br />The thing that I&#8217;ve been telling myself is that I&#8217;ve got a lot going on already, what with church, kickboxing, a very interesting job, writing these pieces, wanting to spend time with my friends and family, and having many other projects I want to do.<br /><br />In fact, I&#8217;ve felt like I&#8217;ve been doing a crappy job with all of these things because it&#8217;s difficult to give them the focus and time that they deserve.<br /><h3>Perfectionism</h3>Regular readers of this blog know very well that I&#8217;m not suffering from crippling perfectionism. &nbsp;I publish a lot of things that are much less good than I&#8217;d like them to be, and quite a few blog posts that I think are fundamentally flawed. &nbsp;Sorry.<br /><br />Even so, I often let the desire for the perfect defeat the good. &nbsp;Let&#8217;s take going to the gym as an example again (it&#8217;s been on my mind). &nbsp;The best time to go is in the afternoon, and there are some dangers associated with heavy lifting in the morning. &nbsp;But going after work would put me in the rush, and going in the middle of the work afternoon would introduce a two hour interruption to my day. &nbsp;So better not to go at all, right?<br /><br />As thin as one-ply tissue paper that&#8217;s just been used.<br /><h3>Lack of structured rest</h3>Resting and relaxing properly is a necessary part of living life to the full. When I don&#8217;t get enough rest, eventually my brain starts working begrudgingly and my body starts to say &#8220;no&#8221;.<br /><br />If I get much less than seven hours sleep, I work much less effectively. Also, it&#8217;s very easy for me to drink enough that everything the next day is significantly harder than it is otherwise.<br /><br />I&#8217;m not saying it&#8217;s always culpable Sloth when I stay up late or when I go out celebrating: life is more than work or duty. &nbsp;But some times I know that the consequence will be a whole day when I need to be productive and all I&#8217;ll be good for is watching cat videos.<br /><h3>Lack of attention</h3>We don&#8217;t fall into attentiveness, we have to pay it. &nbsp;It takes effort, and so much of the time I can&#8217;t be bothered to spend that effort.<br /><br />I really hate it when I do this, because it means doing two things crappily at the same time. &nbsp;I&#8217;m only partly enjoying whatever talk or meeting or conversation I&#8217;m in, and I&#8217;m only partly enjoying whatever email / daydream / conversation / article I&#8217;m distracting myself with. &nbsp;There&#8217;s a real sense in which a lack of attention denies life.<br /><h3>Procrastination</h3>Perhaps the most frequent way I&#8217;m lazy is by always picking the easiest and most pleasurable item on my todo list. &nbsp;I should be doing this thing that&#8217;s important and has a deadline, but that involves something awkward like learning or having a confrontational conversation or getting off the couch, so instead I&#8217;m doing to read this paper on scalable computing that I&#8217;ve been wanting to read for ages.<br /><br />This one is insidious because I can spend a whole day doing productive work, sometimes even work that&#8217;s beneficial to others, but still actually be lazy, because I&#8217;m avoiding things of greater importance or urgency.<br /><h3>Not taking initiative</h3>The canonical example is being out at UDS with a group of people who want to go to dinner but as a mass are entirely incapable of actually making it happen.<br /><br />When I see this happen, I almost always think &#8220;You know, if I just stepped up and took charge, they&#8217;d probably be grateful, and we&#8217;d get to eat sooner.&#8221; And then I think, &#8220;I&#8217;ve spent the whole day talking and listening and explaining and negotiating. &nbsp;Someone else can sort it out.&#8221;<br /><br />Another example: I&#8217;m writing this in Markdown right now. &nbsp;I&#8217;ll then paste it into blogger and then edit it to be formatted correctly. &nbsp;That&#8217;s stupid work for a human being to do, and I really ought to make a machine that does it for me. &nbsp;But that would involve holding myself to a higher standard, and switching into a different mode of work, and &#8230;<br /><h3>Number 7</h3>And you know what, sometimes I simply can&#8217;t be arsed.<br /><br /><span style="font-size: 13px;">This post is part of the&nbsp;</span><a href="http://life.mumak.net/2013/01/the-alphabet-supremacy.html" style="font-size: 13px;">Alphabet Supremacy</a><span style="font-size: 13px;">&nbsp;project, a collaboration between myself and&nbsp;</span><a href="http://life.metagnome.net/" style="font-size: 13px;">Bice Dibley</a><span style="font-size: 13px;">. Next week&#8217;s word is &#8220;music&#8221;.</span><br /></div>
]]>
		</content>
	</entry>
	
	<entry>
		
			<title type="html"><![CDATA[Logic]]></title>
		
		<link href="http://life.mumak.net/2013/06/logic.html"/>
		<updated>2013-06-09T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
		<id>http://life.mumak.net/2013/06/logic</id>
		<content type="html">
			<![CDATA[
				
					<p></p>
				
			]]>
			<![CDATA[<div class='post'>
<span style="background-color: white; font-family: Helvetica, arial, sans-serif; font-size: 14px; line-height: 22px;">You might remember a few weeks ago, I wrote that&nbsp;</span><a href="http://life.mumak.net/2013/02/things-i-wish-we-were-taught-in-school.html" style="background-color: white; color: #4183c4; font-family: Helvetica, arial, sans-serif; font-size: 14px; line-height: 22px; max-width: 100%;" target="_blank">I wished I learned more about logic at school</a><span style="background-color: white; font-family: Helvetica, arial, sans-serif; font-size: 14px; line-height: 22px;">, particularly applying logic to prose arguments about complex and messy topics.</span><br /><div style="background-color: white; font-family: Helvetica, arial, sans-serif; font-size: 14px; line-height: 22px; margin-bottom: 15px; margin-top: 15px; max-width: 100%;">I&#8217;ve actually done a little bit of reading in this area, particularly&nbsp;<a href="http://www.amazon.co.uk/Straight-Crooked-Thinking-Yourself-ebook/dp/B004YD1S1E/ref=sr_1_1?ie=UTF8&amp;qid=1370795838&amp;sr=8-1&amp;keywords=straight+and+crooked+thinking" style="color: #4183c4; max-width: 100%;" target="_blank">Straight and Crooked Thinking</a>by Robert Thouless, which is a top notch book on the subject, filled with lots of examples.</div><div style="background-color: white; font-family: Helvetica, arial, sans-serif; font-size: 14px; line-height: 22px; margin-bottom: 15px; margin-top: 15px; max-width: 100%;">You can walk away from a book like that feeling fully armed to face the mountebanks, quacks, hucksters and purveyors of snake oil who are out there trying to prey on your gullibility with beguiling words and smooth ways. Or perhaps with your newly sharpened logical razor, you will make better decisions, using the powers of science and reason to solve all of the problems that face you. Just like Doctor Who.</div><div style="background-color: white; font-family: Helvetica, arial, sans-serif; font-size: 14px; line-height: 22px; margin-bottom: 15px; margin-top: 15px; max-width: 100%;">I certainly felt that way. Sadly, I didn&#8217;t live up to my visions of logical glory. Stephen Bond has written a&nbsp;<a href="http://plover.net/~bonds/bdksucks.html" style="color: #4183c4; max-width: 100%;" target="_blank">great piece</a>&nbsp;about this focusing on the moral side of things. I&#8217;d like to take a look at some of the pragmatic failure modes, focusing on three ways I&#8217;ve screwed up by being too zealous with my baloney detection kit.</div><h3>Awkward silence</h3><div style="background-color: white; font-family: Helvetica, arial, sans-serif; font-size: 14px; line-height: 22px; margin-bottom: 15px; margin-top: 15px; max-width: 100%;">Once I became conscious of all of the ways I could be wrong, suddenly it became very hard to say anything at all.</div><div style="background-color: white; font-family: Helvetica, arial, sans-serif; font-size: 14px; line-height: 22px; margin-bottom: 15px; margin-top: 15px; max-width: 100%;">Was I really sure that the thing I was saying was true? How did I know? Did I use emotional language to make my point? Was I implying that a thing was true of all people when it was really only true of some?</div><div style="background-color: white; font-family: Helvetica, arial, sans-serif; font-size: 14px; line-height: 22px; margin-bottom: 15px; margin-top: 15px; max-width: 100%;">Much easier to say nothing at all.</div><div style="background-color: white; font-family: Helvetica, arial, sans-serif; font-size: 14px; line-height: 22px; margin-bottom: 15px; margin-top: 15px; max-width: 100%;">Maybe that&#8217;s fine. I talk too much anyway, and it&#8217;s probably good to have something to staunch the flow.</div><div style="background-color: white; font-family: Helvetica, arial, sans-serif; font-size: 14px; line-height: 22px; margin-bottom: 15px; margin-top: 15px; max-width: 100%;">On the other hand, in some kinds of discussions – &#8220;crucial&#8221; confrontations, design critiques, brainstorming – what most parties want isn&#8217;t perfectly formed logical assertions, but simply to get everyone&#8217;s thoughts and questions on the table.</div><h3>Selective application</h3><div style="background-color: white; font-family: Helvetica, arial, sans-serif; font-size: 14px; line-height: 22px; margin-bottom: 15px; margin-top: 15px; max-width: 100%;">It turns out I&#8217;m not great at tearing my own treasured beliefs to shreds. All of these logical tools are so much easier for me to apply when it&#8217;s about something I already disagree with.</div><div style="background-color: white; font-family: Helvetica, arial, sans-serif; font-size: 14px; line-height: 22px; margin-bottom: 15px; margin-top: 15px; max-width: 100%;">So if someone posts a thing about how shared mutable state is great, or how we should rewrite a functioning piece of software in a different language, or why we should kick out all of the immigrants, I whip out my baloney detection kit and point out their invalid sampling, their circular arguments, their appeals to moderation (also a fallacy!), their arguments of the beard and have at them. It&#8217;s great fun. I doubt it actually helps anyone, least of all me.</div><div style="background-color: white; font-family: Helvetica, arial, sans-serif; font-size: 14px; line-height: 22px; margin-bottom: 15px; margin-top: 15px; max-width: 100%;">This is double-edged suck. Not only do I miss the opportunity to learn from people who disagree with me, but I also miss the chance to gain a deeper understanding of the basis of my own opinions. If a belief is worth holding, it ought to be able to withstand a bit of rigorous scrutiny.</div><h3>Colossal prat</h3><div style="background-color: white; font-family: Helvetica, arial, sans-serif; font-size: 14px; line-height: 22px; margin-bottom: 15px; margin-top: 15px; max-width: 100%;">Finally, rather than being a champion of enlightenment, I found it way too easy to end up being a colossal prat.</div><div style="background-color: white; font-family: Helvetica, arial, sans-serif; font-size: 14px; line-height: 22px; margin-bottom: 15px; margin-top: 15px; max-width: 100%;">So often, people are just trying to express a half-formed idea and want their interlocutors to help it grow into something solid. Sometimes, they just want to have a conversation.</div><div style="background-color: white; font-family: Helvetica, arial, sans-serif; font-size: 14px; line-height: 22px; margin-bottom: 15px; margin-top: 15px; max-width: 100%;">I know this is really obvious to most of you, but sometimes I do forget. The other day, we were talking on IRC about how so much software sucks. Onei person chimed in, saying &#8220;it&#8217;s kind of silly to be angry for expecting too much&#8221;.</div><div style="background-color: white; font-family: Helvetica, arial, sans-serif; font-size: 14px; line-height: 22px; margin-bottom: 15px; margin-top: 15px; max-width: 100%;">Gasp! He uttered a tautology! Of course it&#8217;s silly to be angry for expecting too much, that&#8217;s precisely what &#8220;too much&#8221; means. Strictly speaking the sentence adds nothing to the conversation.</div><div style="background-color: white; font-family: Helvetica, arial, sans-serif; font-size: 14px; line-height: 22px; margin-bottom: 15px; margin-top: 15px; max-width: 100%;">And yet, I knew what he meant. He meant that our expectations were too high and we should lower them and be happier, gentler people. But rather than agreeing or disagreeing with his actual point, I decided to put on my Logic Pants and point out his mistake.</div><div style="background-color: white; font-family: Helvetica, arial, sans-serif; font-size: 14px; line-height: 22px; margin-bottom: 15px; margin-top: 15px; max-width: 100%;">Happily, he seemed to take it gracefully and his follow-up rephrasing carried genuine content. I still felt like a prat though.</div><h3>Conclusion</h3><div style="background-color: white; font-family: Helvetica, arial, sans-serif; font-size: 14px; line-height: 22px; margin-bottom: 15px; margin-top: 15px; max-width: 100%;">I&#8217;m not trying to excuse sloppy thinking, nor do I want to set up a false dichotomy between &#8220;logical&#8221; and &#8220;useful&#8221;. However, sometimes I can get more done, contribute more effectively and learn better from others when I relax the rigour a little. And that&#8217;s not unreasonable, is it?<br /><br /><span style="font-family: Helvetica; font-size: 13px; line-height: normal;">This post is part of the&nbsp;</span><a href="http://life.mumak.net/2013/01/the-alphabet-supremacy.html" style="font-family: Helvetica; font-size: 13px; line-height: normal;">Alphabet Supremacy</a><span style="font-family: Helvetica; font-size: 13px; line-height: normal;">&nbsp;project, a collaboration between myself and&nbsp;</span><a href="http://life.metagnome.net/" style="font-family: Helvetica; font-size: 13px; line-height: normal;">Bice Dibley</a><span style="font-family: Helvetica; font-size: 13px; line-height: normal;">. He chooses next week&#8217;s word.</span></div></div>
]]>
		</content>
	</entry>
	
	<entry>
		
			<title type="html"><![CDATA[Keepsake]]></title>
		
		<link href="http://life.mumak.net/2013/06/keepsake.html"/>
		<updated>2013-06-02T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
		<id>http://life.mumak.net/2013/06/keepsake</id>
		<content type="html">
			<![CDATA[
				
					<p></p>
				
			]]>
			<![CDATA[<div class='post'>
A tour of a few keepsakes I have.<br /><br /><b>Lizzie</b><br /><br />When my sister Lizzie came back from her honeymoon, she brought me a small wooden carving of a man sitting down, his head tilted to the side and resting on the palm of his hand.<br /><br />He doesn&#8217;t have any facial features, but I&#8217;ve always imagined him to be quite glum, as if he has spent a long time alone chasing his thoughts and is pretending not to notice that they never go anywhere.<br /><br />When the gift was given, I had felt that way quite a lot of the time for quite a while, and it was about as much fun as it sounds. &nbsp;It&#8217;s just a little token and it&#8217;s likely I&#8217;m reading way too much into the gift (although maybe not!) but I was quite touched when I received it, and it&#8217;s sitting on our mantelpiece today.<br /><br /><b>Martin</b><br /><br />My primary school education was a little bit weird. &nbsp;It took a couple of years for everyone to agree that the standard curriculum was doing me more harm than good and to decide what to do about it. &nbsp;In the end, I was taken out of regular classes, became &#8220;non-graded&#8221; and was assigned to a teacher named Martin Chance. &nbsp;Whichever class he taught, I&#8217;d be there in the back, sometimes working with the class but mostly doing something else that he had assigned.<br /><br />He taught me Go, tried valiantly to make me a good chess player, insisted that I read things I didn&#8217;t like, which at the time included &#8220;The Tempest&#8221;, &#8220;A Coral Island&#8221; and &#8220;War of the Worlds&#8221;. &nbsp;Where I wanted to focus on maths and programming, Martin insisted on teaching me philosophy, history and geography.<br /><br />Martin became a friend of the family, and after I finished primary school I&#8217;d still go over to his place to talk or to mow the lawn or whatever. &nbsp;Although in later years we drifted apart, I still consider him a great friend and can&#8217;t help but acknowledge the great positive influence he has been in my life.<br /><br />Which is pretty much the reason I keep a small wooden box with a pair of Baoding balls in it.<br /><br /><b>Tilly</b><br /><br />I love my nieces, and probably the worst thing about being an expat is that I only get to see them very rarely. &nbsp;The main reason I still have a Facebook account is because that&#8217;s the place I&#8217;m most likely to find new photos of them.<br /><br />We&#8217;ve yet to receive anything from Georgia, our youngest niece, but if you looked around our flat for long enough you would find a drawing of Aunty Jolie &amp; myself, standing underneath a London rainbow next to some flowers, as well as a cardboard canary, with wings made by cutting around the outlines of a pair of small hands.<br /><br /><b>Bice</b><br /><br />(Ah ha ha! Hoisted by your own petard!)<br /><br />Because sometimes it&#8217;s okay to conform unthinkingly to your gender stereotype, I haven&#8217;t owned a fluffy stuffed toy in years. &nbsp;I have Bice to thank for changing that.<br /><br />For a while, I&#8217;ve wanted to own a dog – a big dog, like a Newfoundland Terrier. &nbsp;But for all of that time, I haven&#8217;t felt as if I could responsibly own one. &nbsp;As a renter, I didn&#8217;t want to be forced to move somewhere I couldn&#8217;t have pets and I used to travel quite a lot for work.<br /><br />I explained this to Bice once. &nbsp;The way I put it was that my five year plan was to own a dog, and that getting a mortgage was a step in the middle.<br /><br />I also explained it to Joliette while we were courting each other. &nbsp;It&#8217;s important to make sure that you have the same priorities before making a commitment, no? &nbsp;She isn&#8217;t as set on a Newfie as I am, but we are both equally torn between our desire to keep living centrally in London and for a big, slobbering, canine friend.<br /><br />When Bice visited for our wedding, he somehow remembered our offhand conversation, and brought us a plush black Newfoundland, whom Jolie &amp; I promptly christened Mortgage.<br /><br /><br /><span style="font-size: 13px;">This post is part of the&nbsp;</span><a href="http://life.mumak.net/2013/01/the-alphabet-supremacy.html" style="font-size: 13px;">Alphabet Supremacy</a><span style="font-size: 13px;">&nbsp;project, a collaboration between myself and&nbsp;</span><a href="http://life.metagnome.net/" style="font-size: 13px;">Bice Dibley</a><span style="font-size: 13px;">. Next week&#8217;s word is &#8220;logic&#8221;.</span></div>
<h2>Comments</h2>
<div class='comments'>
<div class='comment'>
<div class='author'>JB<span class='comment-date'> on 2013-06-02 23:24</span></div>
<div class='content'>
Getting a mortgage in order to own a dog at first sounds silly&#8230; but it&#39;s not.</div>
</div>
<div class='comment'>
<div class='author'>JB<span class='comment-date'> on 2013-06-02 23:23</span></div>
<div class='content'>
This comment has been removed by the author.</div>
</div>
</div>
]]>
		</content>
	</entry>
	
	<entry>
		
			<title type="html"><![CDATA[Just]]></title>
		
		<link href="http://life.mumak.net/2013/05/just.html"/>
		<updated>2013-05-19T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
		<id>http://life.mumak.net/2013/05/just</id>
		<content type="html">
			<![CDATA[
				
					<p></p>
				
			]]>
			<![CDATA[<div class='post'>
<br />I think most readers of this blog have already heard of <a href="http://hpmor.com/"><i>Harry Potter and the Methods of Rationality</i></a>. It&#8217;s a long-running Harry Potter fanfic where our hero isn&#8217;t the slightly dopey jock aristocrat of Rowling&#8217;s books, but is instead a hyper-intelligent bookish kid with a penchant for logic, reason, the scientific method and world domination.<br /><br />If you haven&#8217;t read it, it&#8217;s perhaps not good enough to bump to the top of your queue, but is certainly a pleasant way of spending a long haul flight. Certainly I&#8217;ve read more than one published work of fiction that was far preachier and much less fun to read.<br /><br />It&#8217;s written by a chap named Eliezer Yudkowsky who helped found <a href="http://lesswrong.com/">Less Wrong</a>, a website notionally aimed at helping you &amp; I be more rational. There&#8217;s some pretty good stuff there, as well as plenty of things to take issue with. Others have done so <a href="http://plover.net/~bonds/cultofbayes.html">much better than I could</a>, but I&#8217;ve yet to read anything to take issue with the thing that bugs me the most: utilitarianism.<br /><br />Their pitch is that a rational agent will (and should? is &#8220;should&#8221; a thing?) choose a course of action most likely to bring about the greatest good for the greatest number. Simple enough, and a useful decision making tool for questions like &#8220;Should I bring a blue cheese or a bottle of wine to dinner?&#8221; or &#8220;Should we compel people to purchase insurance?&#8221;.<br /><br />Harry exemplifies this throughout &#8220;the Methods of Rationality&#8221;. He is remarkably consistent in choosing his actions based on his best understanding of the greatest good for the greatest number. He even has a crisis of conscience when he become unsure of whether carrots are sentient.<br /><br />Except, well, he&#8217;s not. At least, I don&#8217;t think he is.<br /><br />My suspicions were first raised in Azkaban. When Harry visits there and realizes what&#8217;s going on, he reacts with moral fury. Azkaban is not simply irrational, it is simply wrong for human beings to be treated this way. Deontological ethics if ever I heard any. After all, it&#8217;s entirely possible that keeping a subset of humanity locked up in awful conditions will maximize utility, no?<br /><br />But reading up on consequentialist ethics for this piece, I can see a way to restore him to utilitarian purity. Harry&#8217;s objection is not simply that it&#8217;s a prison, but one where <a href="http://hpmor.com/chapter/62">the prisoners are tortured to death</a>. He reacts with such passion because there&#8217;d be more utility if they weren&#8217;t being tortured, and either he doesn&#8217;t buy the argument that Dementor wardens is the only way to safely guard them, or he thinks that an ineffective prison would be better than such one staffed by Dementors.<br /><br />Even earlier than Azkaban, but only discovered by me while working on this piece, there&#8217;s a scene where <a href="http://hpmor.com/chapter/47">Draco tries to enlist Harry to aide him against the murderer of Draco&#8217;s mother</a>, who was burnt alive. Harry eventually agrees to make this person his enemy, given five conditions.<br /><br />One of the conditions is that the deal might be off if the killing were a revenge killing. That is, if Narcissa did something awful. Why?<br /><blockquote class="tr_bq">Because then it was still wrong for them to burn her, they still should&#8217;ve just killed her without pain; but it wasn&#8217;t evil the same way as if she was just Lucius&#8217;s love who never did anything herself, like you said.</blockquote>I agree, but my ethics are sloppy and largely deontological. How does it make sense for a utilitarian to decide whether or not to administer justice based on the flavour of evil in the motive?<br /><br />Somewhat annoyingly, a Google search for &#8220;mens rea utilitarian&#8221; reveals the answer on a <a href="http://quizlet.com/7154997/crim-law-midterm-mens-rea-flash-cards/">criminal law mid-term flash card</a>.<br /><blockquote class="tr_bq">A person who commits the actus reus [guilty act] of an offense without a mens rea [guilty mind] is not dangerous, could not have been deterred, and is not in need of reform, therefore, their punishment would be counterutilitarian.</blockquote>Perhaps this is what Harry is thinking of. I&#8217;m sceptical though. The language that Harry uses in his negotiations with Draco are clearly not consequentialist, but primarily concerned with doing what is right, and throughout the <i>Methods of Rationality</i>, Yudkowsky freeloads off deontological sentiment while espousing a consequentialist worldview.<br /><br />Even so, it&#8217;s a much more difficult opinion to skewer than I had imagined, which rather sabotages my plans to end this with a glib note about how truly <i>just</i> punishment must be at least partly retributive, per C. S. Lewis&#8217;s essay on the&nbsp;<a href="http://www.angelfire.com/pro/lewiscs/humanitarian.html">Humanitarian Theory of Punishment</a>.<br /><br />Clearly I&#8217;m going to have to go back to my books and figure out just what I actually think. What a bother.<br /><br /><span style="font-size: 13px;">This post is part of the&nbsp;</span><a href="http://life.mumak.net/2013/01/the-alphabet-supremacy.html" style="font-size: 13px;">Alphabet Supremacy</a><span style="font-size: 13px;">&nbsp;project, a collaboration between myself and&nbsp;</span><a href="http://life.metagnome.net/" style="font-size: 13px;">Bice Dibley</a><span style="font-size: 13px;">. Next week&#8217;s word is &#8220;key&#8221;.</span></div>
]]>
		</content>
	</entry>
	
	<entry>
		
			<title type="html"><![CDATA[Jubilee]]></title>
		
		<link href="http://life.mumak.net/2013/05/jubilee.html"/>
		<updated>2013-05-12T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
		<id>http://life.mumak.net/2013/05/jubilee</id>
		<content type="html">
			<![CDATA[
				
					<p></p>
				
			]]>
			<![CDATA[<div class='post'>
How would we live if we knew that sometime in our life, all of our debt would be cancelled? If there was a known date in the future when everything we owe to anyone else would be forgotten, and when we would be obliged to forgive anything anyone owed us?<br /><br />That is the gist of the Year of Jubilee, which you can read all about in <a href="http://www.biblegateway.com/passage/?search=Leviticus%2025%20&amp;version=NIV">Leviticus 25</a>&nbsp;if you should so desire. Every fifty years, debts are forgiven, slaves are freed, land is returned to its original owners, the slate is wiped clean.<br /><br /><br />This makes a lot of sense. Unless you are living in&nbsp;<a href="http://www.amazon.co.uk/Atlas-Shrugged-Centennial-Edition-ebook/dp/B003V8B5XO/">a fictional paradise</a>, poverty can come from things other than laziness, incompetence, and government intervention: accidents happen, people get sick, and land is not always abundant. When such things happen – and they do, over and over – the poor sell off their land, or simply borrow money from the rich. This eases their current situation but reduces their income, leaving them more vulnerable to the next disaster.<br /><br /><br /><br />Thus, most Jubilee laws come with words about how they protect widows and orphans, and the poor from the rich. They rebalance society, they – I&#8217;ve never felt my lack of an economic education more keenly than now – restore to the workers the ownership of the means of production.<br /><br /><br />That said, it&#8217;s not clear whether the law was ever implemented. The Biblical record is silent (to my knowledge), and we&#8217;re not exactly drowning in extra-biblical sources for ancient Israeli history. To my modern sensibility, the idea is unsettling. Wouldn&#8217;t people just go on massive credit card sprees? Would it become impossible to get a mortgage in year forty-nine? As an Australian, it&#8217;s even slightly alarming. Just who are the original owners to whom land should be returned?<br /><br />At least <a href="http://michael-hudson.com/wp-content/uploads/2010/03/HudsonLostTradition.pdf">one guy on the Internet</a> claims there are evidences of similar laws &amp; decrees elsewhere in the Near East, and thus that even if Israel never implemented a Jubilee, it&#8217;s likely that Babylon and Sumer did.<br /><br />David Graeber, author of <i><a href="http://www.amazon.co.uk/Debt-First-000-Years-ebook/dp/B00513DGIO/">Debt: The First 5,000 Years</a>&nbsp;</i>(the most thought-provoking book I read in 2012), argues that we should institute a Jubilee now, for both international debt and consumer debt. To those who say &#8220;surely one has to pay ones debts&#8221;, <a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=CZIINXhGDcs">he points out</a> that part of the deal of lending money out at interest is that you might not ever get your money back. When you spot a struggling third world country a couple of billion, only to see them have a military coup followed by years of famine, well, perhaps it&#8217;s time to write that one off, rather than demand interest payments from the destitute nation for the next few decades. Oh to be able to run an experimental fork of the world economy.<br /><br />If we just did it for consumer debt in a rich nation, such as Britain, and we somehow figured out to whom land ought to return – a tricky question that Graeber avoids – what would happen next?<br /><br />My imagination fails me. Cynically, I think there&#8217;d be a temporary dip in the finance sector until the City boys figured out how to create an instrument that lasted over the Jubilee. In a sense, a debt is just a precisely defined obligation, just information. It&#8217;s not a coincidence that the earliest writing we have are records of credit. To erase debt in Sumer, they literally washed the tablets, smoothing the cuneiform dimples from it until it was just clay. Getting rid of information these days is trickier.<br /><br />Got any thoughts yourself? I&#8217;m very interested in this topic but, as mentioned, have no idea what I&#8217;m talking about. Feel free to comment here or on G+.<br /><br /><span style="font-size: 13px;">This post is part of the&nbsp;</span><a href="http://life.mumak.net/2013/01/the-alphabet-supremacy.html" style="font-size: 13px;">Alphabet Supremacy</a><span style="font-size: 13px;">&nbsp;project, a collaboration between myself and&nbsp;</span><a href="http://life.metagnome.net/" style="font-size: 13px;">Bice Dibley</a><span style="font-size: 13px;">.</span></div>
]]>
		</content>
	</entry>
	
	<entry>
		
			<title type="html"><![CDATA[Indifference]]></title>
		
		<link href="http://life.mumak.net/2013/05/indifference.html"/>
		<updated>2013-05-05T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
		<id>http://life.mumak.net/2013/05/indifference</id>
		<content type="html">
			<![CDATA[
				
					<p></p>
				
			]]>
			<![CDATA[<div class='post'>
Arnold the Wanderer reclined back in his chair, hugging a hot cup of tea with his hands. &nbsp;It wasn&#8217;t as he normally liked it, but it was hot, and that was an important thing. &#8220;It&#8217;s not that I&#8217;m at all ungrateful for your hospitality,&#8221; he said, &#8220;but what or who exactly is this temple for?&#8221;<br /><br />The monk&#8217;s face lit up with a special glee. &#8220;Oh, no, not at all. &nbsp;We welcome the chance to share the particularities of our message with any who earnestly seek the path&#8221;.<br /><br />&#8220;I wouldn&#8217;t quite call myself a seeker, you know. Just a fellow who&#8217;s a bit baffled.&#8221;<br /><br />&#8220;Ah, yes,&#8221; the monk spread his hands and smiled, relishing a rare chance to nod sagely, &#8220;all too well do I remember the confusion of the unenlightened.&#8221;<br /><br />&#8220;No, no – well, yes, maybe – but what religion are you?&#8221;<br /><br />&#8220;We are the followers of Bel Shang-Gur, and we strive to walk in his path.&#8221;<br /><br />Arnold had wandered the earth for years, and had spoken to many mystics, demagogues, hermits, hierophants and sarcedotes. He had never heard of Bel Shang-Gur, and said as much.<br /><br />&#8220;Bel Shang-Gur was originally not a holy man, but a prosperous merchant in a city far south of here. One afternoon, as he was walking down its streets, arm in arm with his wife, she, in her ignorance, asked him the First Unanswerable Question, planting the seed of our whole order.<br /><br />&#8216;What would you like to do tonight?&#8217;<br /><br />As Bel Shang-Gur heard those words, he saw a single blossom fall from one of the linden trees that lined the street. Although he had heard those words hundreds of times before, a new and spiritual understanding dawned within him.<br /><br />&#8216;I don&#8217;t know, what would you like to do?&#8217;<br /><br />On instinct! So early! Simple words, and yet so profound! He had discovered the Second Unanswerable Question, the second vertex of the mystery on which our order is founded.&#8221;<br /><br />Arnold the Wanderer did his best to nod sagely.<br /><br />&#8220;Does your neck trouble you, seeker?&#8221;<br /><br />&#8220;Uh, no. Carry on.&#8221;<br /><br />The monk was frothing over like a glass of beer with a sugar cube in. &#8220;He saw that it was his will – to want or to not want – that divided him from the cosmos. That the blossom, resigned to its fate and carried by the wind was truly at peace. From that day forth, he resolved to cultivate an indifference to all things, and to pass on this serenity to all who would listen.&#8221;<br /><br />&#8220;Here in Abbey of the Holy Apathy, we train ourselves to follow his path. First, we rid ourselves of preference and inclination, then anticipation and nostalgia, then appetite and desire, and finally attaining to a volitional void. &nbsp;&#8216;Blessed is he who truly doesn&#8217;t mind either way&#8217;.&#8221;<br /><br />&#8220;Truly, your way is an arduous one.&#8221;<br /><br />&#8220;Oh yes! For the first year, our brother monks are instructed to mispronounce our names. It is only when the vexation is cleansed from our hearts that we are permitted to truly begin as novitiates.&#8221;<br /><br />&#8220;And have you gone far on your journey to enlightenment?&#8221;<br /><br />The monk visibly slumped. &#8220;It is a hard path to walk. Just yesterday, I couldn&#8217;t remember what I had for breakfast, which was a big step for me. I had porridge today though. Brother Kells most days can&#8217;t remember whether he even had breakfast, the jammy bastard.&#8221;<br /><br />Seeing Arnold&#8217;s&nbsp;querulous&nbsp;gaze, the monk remembered himself and rose serenely. &#8220;Seeker, would you like another cup of tea?&#8221;<br /><br />&#8220;Oh, yes please! But could I have it with two sugars this time?&#8221; &nbsp;The monk&#8217;s face turned ashen.<br /><br />&#8220;Dark indeed are the ways of the unenlightened.&#8221;<br /><div><br /></div><span style="font-size: 13px;">This post is part of the&nbsp;</span><a href="http://life.mumak.net/2013/01/the-alphabet-supremacy.html" style="font-size: 13px;">Alphabet Supremacy</a><span style="font-size: 13px;">&nbsp;project, a collaboration between myself and&nbsp;</span><a href="http://life.metagnome.net/" style="font-size: 13px;">Bice Dibley</a><span style="font-size: 13px;">. Next week&#8217;s word is Jubilee.</span></div>
]]>
		</content>
	</entry>
	
	<entry>
		
			<title type="html"><![CDATA[Island]]></title>
		
		<link href="http://life.mumak.net/2013/04/island.html"/>
		<updated>2013-04-28T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
		<id>http://life.mumak.net/2013/04/island</id>
		<content type="html">
			<![CDATA[
				
					<p></p>
				
			]]>
			<![CDATA[<div class='post'>
If I were to be marooned on a desert island and were allowed a single physical object to console me in my exile, that object would almost definitely be underpants. Should my captors show me mercy and treat clothes as a given, then I would probably ask for my Kindle. And a solar-powered USB charger, of course. Although why they would deign to let me take an item onto this rocky outcrop of doom is as much a mystery to me as why they would stick me there in the first place. But if it were three items, then it would definitely be my Kindle, a charger, and spare set of clean pants.<br /><br />Taking a Kindle renders the traditional dinner party question moot. The whole point – other than allowing everyone at the table a chance to briefly fantasize about escaping the present company – is to learn something of your companions. When someone chooses say, the Bible, <i>Crime and Punishment</i>, and a Wodehouse omnibus, you learn that he (or she – but you can probably guess in this case who the hypothetical someone actually is), then you learn that he (or she) is a devout person with a passion for redemption narratives and tweed-core comedy. Or at least that this is what he wishes you to think of him.<br /><br />When our unlucky fellow diner picks a Kindle, you don&#8217;t get any of that. The best we can tell is that by picking an ebook reader over an iPod that he&#8217;s probably not a music person. Or it could be that he values personal hygiene over a set of headphones. You just can&#8217;t tell.<br /><br />More interesting to me is why we have all been sent to this desert island in the first place under such bizarre terms. How would we get there? <i>Lost</i>&nbsp;notwithstanding, modern communications technology rules out an accidental, Gilligan scenario. There must be some kind of intent. And let&#8217;s face it, whoever is abandoning us to the elements probably doesn&#8217;t exactly have our best interests at heart. Were they benevolent, there&#8217;d be much better ways of expressing it. They could give us an ice cream. Their intent, therefore, must be malicious.<br /><br />But why an island, rather than say, Wolverhampton? Why not just do us in? And why offer us comforts in a way that is both absurdly generous and yet so arbitrarily limited.<br /><br />One of the other guests has to be in on it. This is the only thing that makes sense. This guest employs agents who then strand us in different islands across the globe, making it look to each of us as if he (or she) were a hapless victim. An island, rather than a not particularly interesting city, much reduces the likelihood that we&#8217;ll ever be able to get back and inform on them – assuming any of us figures it out.<br /><br />And, presumably since we&#8217;re all at the same table together, we are all friends, or friends of friends, or (if we&#8217;re particularly unlucky) family. Thus it&#8217;s likely that this Judas in our midst shares kith or kin with us who he&#8217;d rather not bereave. Hence exile, not execution.<br /><br />No other explanation makes any sense.<br /><br />Next time someone asks you this question, be very suspicious. And don&#8217;t forget to ask about the pants. <br /><br /><span style="font-size: 13px;">This post is part of the&nbsp;</span><a href="http://life.mumak.net/2013/01/the-alphabet-supremacy.html" style="font-size: 13px;">Alphabet Supremacy</a><span style="font-size: 13px;">&nbsp;project, a collaboration between myself and&nbsp;</span><a href="http://life.metagnome.net/" style="font-size: 13px;">Bice Dibley</a><span style="font-size: 13px;">.</span></div>
<h2>Comments</h2>
<div class='comments'>
<div class='comment'>
<div class='author'>dbuchan<span class='comment-date'> on 2013-04-29 15:07</span></div>
<div class='content'>
You are to be marooned on a Desert Island with a 1st generation iPod. You are given the chance to rip 11 CDs to .wav format. There are exits to the North and South. To the East is a hand operated moveable-type  press.<br /><br />&gt;&#8230;</div>
</div>
<div class='comment'>
<div class='author'>dbuchan<span class='comment-date'> on 2013-04-29 14:59</span></div>
<div class='content'>
This comment has been removed by the author.</div>
</div>
</div>
]]>
		</content>
	</entry>
	
</feed>
