<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: silly | Echo and Bounce]]></title>
  <link href="http://life.mumak.net/blog/categories/silly/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://life.mumak.net/"/>
  <updated>2013-09-15T12:15:48+01:00</updated>
  <id>http://life.mumak.net/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Jonathan Lange]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Indifference]]></title>
    <link href="http://life.mumak.net/2013/05/05/indifference.html"/>
    <updated>2013-05-05T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://life.mumak.net/2013/05/05/indifference</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<div class='post'>
Arnold the Wanderer reclined back in his chair, hugging a hot cup of tea with his hands. &nbsp;It wasn't as he normally liked it, but it was hot, and that was an important thing. "It's not that I'm at all ungrateful for your hospitality," he said, "but what or who exactly is this temple for?"<br /><br />The monk's face lit up with a special glee. "Oh, no, not at all. &nbsp;We welcome the chance to share the particularities of our message with any who earnestly seek the path".<br /><br />"I wouldn't quite call myself a seeker, you know. Just a fellow who's a bit baffled."<br /><br />"Ah, yes," the monk spread his hands and smiled, relishing a rare chance to nod sagely, "all too well do I remember the confusion of the unenlightened."<br /><br />"No, no – well, yes, maybe – but what religion are you?"<br /><br />"We are the followers of Bel Shang-Gur, and we strive to walk in his path."<br /><br />Arnold had wandered the earth for years, and had spoken to many mystics, demagogues, hermits, hierophants and sarcedotes. He had never heard of Bel Shang-Gur, and said as much.<br /><br />"Bel Shang-Gur was originally not a holy man, but a prosperous merchant in a city far south of here. One afternoon, as he was walking down its streets, arm in arm with his wife, she, in her ignorance, asked him the First Unanswerable Question, planting the seed of our whole order.<br /><br />'What would you like to do tonight?'<br /><br />As Bel Shang-Gur heard those words, he saw a single blossom fall from one of the linden trees that lined the street. Although he had heard those words hundreds of times before, a new and spiritual understanding dawned within him.<br /><br />'I don't know, what would you like to do?'<br /><br />On instinct! So early! Simple words, and yet so profound! He had discovered the Second Unanswerable Question, the second vertex of the mystery on which our order is founded."<br /><br />Arnold the Wanderer did his best to nod sagely.<br /><br />"Does your neck trouble you, seeker?"<br /><br />"Uh, no. Carry on."<br /><br />The monk was frothing over like a glass of beer with a sugar cube in. "He saw that it was his will – to want or to not want – that divided him from the cosmos. That the blossom, resigned to its fate and carried by the wind was truly at peace. From that day forth, he resolved to cultivate an indifference to all things, and to pass on this serenity to all who would listen."<br /><br />"Here in Abbey of the Holy Apathy, we train ourselves to follow his path. First, we rid ourselves of preference and inclination, then anticipation and nostalgia, then appetite and desire, and finally attaining to a volitional void. &nbsp;'Blessed is he who truly doesn't mind either way'."<br /><br />"Truly, your way is an arduous one."<br /><br />"Oh yes! For the first year, our brother monks are instructed to mispronounce our names. It is only when the vexation is cleansed from our hearts that we are permitted to truly begin as novitiates."<br /><br />"And have you gone far on your journey to enlightenment?"<br /><br />The monk visibly slumped. "It is a hard path to walk. Just yesterday, I couldn't remember what I had for breakfast, which was a big step for me. I had porridge today though. Brother Kells most days can't remember whether he even had breakfast, the jammy bastard."<br /><br />Seeing Arnold's&nbsp;querulous&nbsp;gaze, the monk remembered himself and rose serenely. "Seeker, would you like another cup of tea?"<br /><br />"Oh, yes please! But could I have it with two sugars this time?" &nbsp;The monk's face turned ashen.<br /><br />"Dark indeed are the ways of the unenlightened."<br /><div><br /></div><span style="font-size: 13px;">This post is part of the&nbsp;</span><a href="http://life.mumak.net/2013/01/the-alphabet-supremacy.html" style="font-size: 13px;">Alphabet Supremacy</a><span style="font-size: 13px;">&nbsp;project, a collaboration between myself and&nbsp;</span><a href="http://life.metagnome.net/" style="font-size: 13px;">Bice Dibley</a><span style="font-size: 13px;">. Next week's word is Jubilee.</span></div>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Island]]></title>
    <link href="http://life.mumak.net/2013/04/28/island.html"/>
    <updated>2013-04-28T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://life.mumak.net/2013/04/28/island</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<div class='post'>
If I were to be marooned on a desert island and were allowed a single physical object to console me in my exile, that object would almost definitely be underpants. Should my captors show me mercy and treat clothes as a given, then I would probably ask for my Kindle. And a solar-powered USB charger, of course. Although why they would deign to let me take an item onto this rocky outcrop of doom is as much a mystery to me as why they would stick me there in the first place. But if it were three items, then it would definitely be my Kindle, a charger, and spare set of clean pants.<br /><br />Taking a Kindle renders the traditional dinner party question moot. The whole point – other than allowing everyone at the table a chance to briefly fantasize about escaping the present company – is to learn something of your companions. When someone chooses say, the Bible, <i>Crime and Punishment</i>, and a Wodehouse omnibus, you learn that he (or she – but you can probably guess in this case who the hypothetical someone actually is), then you learn that he (or she) is a devout person with a passion for redemption narratives and tweed-core comedy. Or at least that this is what he wishes you to think of him.<br /><br />When our unlucky fellow diner picks a Kindle, you don't get any of that. The best we can tell is that by picking an ebook reader over an iPod that he's probably not a music person. Or it could be that he values personal hygiene over a set of headphones. You just can't tell.<br /><br />More interesting to me is why we have all been sent to this desert island in the first place under such bizarre terms. How would we get there? <i>Lost</i>&nbsp;notwithstanding, modern communications technology rules out an accidental, Gilligan scenario. There must be some kind of intent. And let's face it, whoever is abandoning us to the elements probably doesn't exactly have our best interests at heart. Were they benevolent, there'd be much better ways of expressing it. They could give us an ice cream. Their intent, therefore, must be malicious.<br /><br />But why an island, rather than say, Wolverhampton? Why not just do us in? And why offer us comforts in a way that is both absurdly generous and yet so arbitrarily limited.<br /><br />One of the other guests has to be in on it. This is the only thing that makes sense. This guest employs agents who then strand us in different islands across the globe, making it look to each of us as if he (or she) were a hapless victim. An island, rather than a not particularly interesting city, much reduces the likelihood that we'll ever be able to get back and inform on them – assuming any of us figures it out.<br /><br />And, presumably since we're all at the same table together, we are all friends, or friends of friends, or (if we're particularly unlucky) family. Thus it's likely that this Judas in our midst shares kith or kin with us who he'd rather not bereave. Hence exile, not execution.<br /><br />No other explanation makes any sense.<br /><br />Next time someone asks you this question, be very suspicious. And don't forget to ask about the pants. <br /><br /><span style="font-size: 13px;">This post is part of the&nbsp;</span><a href="http://life.mumak.net/2013/01/the-alphabet-supremacy.html" style="font-size: 13px;">Alphabet Supremacy</a><span style="font-size: 13px;">&nbsp;project, a collaboration between myself and&nbsp;</span><a href="http://life.metagnome.net/" style="font-size: 13px;">Bice Dibley</a><span style="font-size: 13px;">.</span></div>


<h2>Comments</h2>


<div class='comments'>
<div class='comment'>
<div class='author'>dbuchan<span class='comment-date'> on 2013-04-29 15:07</span></div>
<div class='content'>
You are to be marooned on a Desert Island with a 1st generation iPod. You are given the chance to rip 11 CDs to .wav format. There are exits to the North and South. To the East is a hand operated moveable-type  press.<br /><br />&gt;...</div>
</div>
<div class='comment'>
<div class='author'>dbuchan<span class='comment-date'> on 2013-04-29 14:59</span></div>
<div class='content'>
This comment has been removed by the author.</div>
</div>
</div>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Super powers]]></title>
    <link href="http://life.mumak.net/2011/07/03/super-powers.html"/>
    <updated>2011-07-03T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://life.mumak.net/2011/07/03/super-powers</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<div class='post'>
It used to be that if you asked me which super-power I wanted, I would tell you, "instantaneous, effortless, accurate, error-free teleportation". Something very much like <a href="http://www.imdb.com/title/tt0489099/">Jumper</a>,&nbsp;except with fewer determined foes and better acting. After all, that would mean no more flights, no more uphill walks, no more being late, no more forgetting things and plenty more holidays.<br /><br />But recently, I've changed my mind. I want to be <i>Video Game Man</i>. I want the super-powers that every video game character actually has that aren't even treated as super-powers.<br /><br /><b>Infinite stamina: </b>Practically every video game character can run, jump, climb and fight forever without becoming tired, experiencing fatigue or slowing down in any way. This would make kickboxing much easier.<br /><br /><b>Self-sustaining:</b>&nbsp;No need to eat, drink or sleep. Well, maybe if I got injured I could eat an apple to cure me. Think of the time saved.<br /><br /><b>Pause:</b>&nbsp;When things get too confusing or fast-paced, or when a difficult decision must be made, I could pause and take as much time as I wanted to think about it. Of course, it would only be thinking.<br /><br /><b>Quick save, quick load:</b>&nbsp;Attempt difficult situations over and over again. Accidental death would not be a problem. Negotiations could be optimized. Future knowledge could be used to enhance past decisions.<br /><br /><b>Friend or foe: </b>Know instantly who the bad guys are. No more moral ambiguity for me, thank you very much!<br /><br /><b>Know thyself:</b>&nbsp;Clear knowledge of all of my own capabilities – no more <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dunning%E2%80%93Kruger_effect">Dunning-Kruger effect</a> for me! – and also of my own status, health, wealth etc. Always obvious what I could improve and how much I could improve.<br /><br /><b>Maps:</b>&nbsp;Always knowing where I am, and where I need to go.<br /><br /><b>Unbreakable: </b>Although I could be injured, it would be impossible to break my limbs, blind me, deafen me, or even slow me down. No possible accident could reduce or remove any of my innate capabilities.<br /><br />Looking over this list, I'm reminded of <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Culture">The Culture</a>, a utopia designed by Iain M. Banks and the little I know of the <a href="http://gamification.org/wiki/Gamification_Books/Reality_Is_Broken">Reality is Broken</a> meme. Which reminds me, most reader of this blog should look at "<a href="http://www.slideshare.net/dings/dont-play-games-with-me-promises-and-pitfalls-of-gameful-design">Don't Play Games With Me</a>".<br /><br />Oh, and if you're able to get me that teleporting gig, I guess I could be convinced to settle for that.</div>


<h2>Comments</h2>


<div class='comments'>
<div class='comment'>
<div class='author'>jml<span class='comment-date'> on 2011-07-04 08:54</span></div>
<div class='content'>
That&#39;s a great list. Of course, I meant <i>practically</i> every video game character.</div>
</div>
<div class='comment'>
<div class='author'>Andrew Durdin<span class='comment-date'> on 2011-07-03 22:48</span></div>
<div class='content'>
Infinite stamina: Battlefield 1942 had stamina that went down when you jumped or ran; when it was empty, you could do neither. Of course, it regenerates, so it is infinite in a way.<br /><br />Self-sustaining: The Ship. You must eat, drink, and use the toilets to survive. Pathologic requires you to eat, drink, and sleep.<br /><br />Pause: I can&#39;t think of a game where not pausing is a notable, intentional feature.<br /><br />Quick save, quick load: Prince of Persia. Not only did it not have quicksave or quickload, it didn&#39;t allow you to save or load at all--you had to complete the game in one hour.<br /><br />Friend or foe: Team Fortress 2. The Spy. He&#39;s behind you.<br /><br />Know thyself: I don&#39;t know any games where you don&#39;t know your status and/or abilities as an intentional, significant feature.<br /><br />Maps: Half-Life 2. No map. No explicit direction of where to go. Of course, being largely linear, you don&#39;t have a lot of choice.<br /><br />Unbreakable: Deus Ex. Your arms, legs, head, and torso sustained damage independently. If your right arm was damaged too far, you could no longer hold a weapon. If both legs were damaged too far, you could no longer walk, but only crawl.</div>
</div>
</div>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
