<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: alphabet-supremacy | Echo and Bounce]]></title>
  <link href="http://life.mumak.net/blog/categories/alphabet-supremacy/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://life.mumak.net/"/>
  <updated>2013-09-15T12:07:21+01:00</updated>
  <id>http://life.mumak.net/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Jonathan Lange]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Serve]]></title>
    <link href="http://life.mumak.net/2013/09/15/serve.html"/>
    <updated>2013-09-15T10:59:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://life.mumak.net/2013/09/15/serve</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>At the moment, this is mucking around with my new way of writing &amp; publishing
blog posts.  Eventually, it will be my alphabet supremacy post for the week.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Rat]]></title>
    <link href="http://life.mumak.net/2013/09/08/rat.html"/>
    <updated>2013-09-08T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://life.mumak.net/2013/09/08/rat</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<div class='post'>
The most visceral memory I have of our trip to New York a couple of weeks ago was on a walk Jolie &amp; I took along the Hudson River.<br /><br />Jolie's friends recommended a bunch of places for us to go see. We were just coming from one of them, a downtown pizza joint that we were slowly waddling away from, leaving behind a confused server and two-thirds of the one and only pizza we ordered. Never order a pizza in America unless there are at least five people around who are willing to give you a hand.<br /><br />Anyway, we're walking down the Hudson, hand-in-hand in the moonlight on our way to a bar that runs in a converted ship, when our path is crossed by this huge rat, just sitting there on the footpath underneath the lights. He didn't look like he was doing much, just chilling out on the river, enjoying the breeze.<br /><br />I actually don't know if he was huge as rats go, since that's the only one I've seen. At first, I thought it was a slightly bulky chihuahua. When we figured out what it was, I was a bit surprised it wasn't busy inducting its turtle friends in the mysteries of ninjitsu. If I'd known, I would have brought them pizza.<br /><br />All the while, it's just sitting there, bold as brass and in no mind to move off the footpath. I hadn't been in New York long enough to insist on my right of way, so I navigated us gently around Master Splinter and resumed our night-time amble toward wobbly-decked drinks, glancing over my shoulder very occasionally – only every three seconds or so – to make sure that no rodent horde was pursuing us.<br /><br />I went to New York with a bit of a preconception that the natives were a bit rude, always in a hurry and more than willing to let you know about it. I didn't find it that way. The dog-sized rat there was easily the rudest New Yorker we met, and he was surprisingly relaxed for a repellent pest that's loathed by all and sundry. I guess he knew there were plenty worse places to be than in Manhattan in the moonlight.<br /><br /><span style="font-size: x-small;">This post is part of the <a href="http://life.mumak.net/2013/01/the-alphabet-supremacy.html">Alphabet Supremacy</a>, a collaboration with <a href="http://life.metagnome.net/">Bice Dibley</a>. Next week's word is "serve".</span></div>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Real]]></title>
    <link href="http://life.mumak.net/2013/09/01/real.html"/>
    <updated>2013-09-01T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://life.mumak.net/2013/09/01/real</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<div class='post'>
"Yes, but things are different in the real world."<br /><br />It's perhaps not <i>the </i>most patronizing thing you can say to someone, but it's close to being the most patronizing thing anyone has said to me. (And I am deeply aware, gentle reader, that it is a privilege for me to be able to say so).<br /><br />When I was at school, I was told the real world was and would be different. After I got online, people reminded me that I needed to spend time in the real world. When I went to university, graduates in full-time employment assumed an air of superior knowledge and sagely informed me that the real world was a different place. When I started work and my colleagues found out I was into open source software, they were happy to tell me how that sort of thing just doesn't work in the real world. When later I started work at Canonical, more than one person would patiently explain to me that sooner or later the pressures of the real world would cause the company to collapse. Now, at Google, I occasionally hear people joke about how it's scary out there in the real world since you have to pay for your food out there.<br /><br />There is exactly one real world. It is the world that we are all living, breathing, eating and sleeping in. We have never in our lives left the real world. Each and every day has been spent within its confines, and it will be so every day until we go to our graves. If it turns out that there is life after that, then that too will be as real as today.<br /><br />Is it possible that the very fabric of the universe shifts and alters at the gates of academia? That friends in the schoolyard mean less than friends in the workplace? Is it really true that being a jerk to someone online is somehow less real than being a jerk to someone standing next to you? Perhaps the laws of physics are suspended at Google, allowing the chefs to conjure food from the ether.<br /><br />No. It's very clear what people actually mean when they say "the real world". They mean "my world", and add to it the sheer effrontery of suggesting that only their experience and the experience of those like them has any validity whatsoever.<br /><br />To tell someone that things are different in the real world is to deny them an authentic experience of reality. That which you have lived through is of less value than that which I have lived through. My concerns have weight, yours are ephemeral. My achievements are solid, yours are imagined. I have the boldness to face the truth and all of its harsh consequences, while you wrap yourself in the warm blanket of pleasant delusion. I matter, you do not.<br /><br />I won't bear any grudge if you use the phrase to compare and contrast obviously imagined worlds to reality. For example, "in Tolkien's Middle Earth, the Silmarils and later the Rings of Power are central, and the lives of thousands turn on them. In the real world, jewellery is rarely that important". If you said that, we might go on to have a spirited discussion about the diamond industry, but I wouldn't object to your phrasing.<br /><br />However, if you say something daft like "Well, all of this open source software is well and good but in the real world we have to think about money", then I'm afraid it's going to be difficult for us to converse further.<br /><br /><span style="background-color: white; color: #333333; font-family: Helvetica; font-size: 13px; text-align: justify;">This post is part of the&nbsp;</span><a href="http://life.mumak.net/2013/01/the-alphabet-supremacy.html" style="-webkit-transition: color 0.3s; background-color: white; color: #009eb8; display: inline; font-family: 'Helvetica Neue Light', HelveticaNeue-Light, 'Helvetica Neue', Helvetica, Arial, sans-serif; font-size: 13px; outline: none; text-align: justify; text-decoration: none; transition: color 0.3s;">Alphabet Supremacy</a><span style="background-color: white; color: #333333; font-family: Helvetica; font-size: 13px; text-align: justify;">&nbsp;project, a collaboration between myself and&nbsp;</span><a href="http://life.metagnome.net/" style="-webkit-transition: color 0.3s; background-color: white; color: #009eb8; display: inline; font-family: 'Helvetica Neue Light', HelveticaNeue-Light, 'Helvetica Neue', Helvetica, Arial, sans-serif; font-size: 13px; outline: none; text-align: justify; text-decoration: none; transition: color 0.3s;">Bice Dibley</a><span style="background-color: white; color: #333333; font-family: Helvetica; font-size: 13px; text-align: justify;">. He chooses next week's word.</span></div>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Quick]]></title>
    <link href="http://life.mumak.net/2013/08/18/quick.html"/>
    <updated>2013-08-18T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://life.mumak.net/2013/08/18/quick</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<div class='post'>
Sometimes I wonder how <i>The Flash</i>&nbsp;can stand it. Not only does he have to struggle through life wearing the world's most ridiculous hat, but he must spend subjective aeons of time forced to watch the rest of us faff.<br /><br />Imagine you're Barry Allen, aka <i>The Flash</i>, and you've got guests over for dinner. It's time for coffee and you realize all of a sudden that you don't have any milk. "No problem", you think, "I'll just nip out to the shops and get some". After all, you sip from the well of the Speed Force, how long could it possibly take?<br /><br />But on the way down the stairs from your apartment, a large couple have decided to stop on the stair case and have an argument about whether or not they actually did buy bacon when they were out at the supermarket. Now, their conversation takes maybe only fifteen or twenty seconds, but if you can move and react a hundred-thousand times faster than a regular human, then that's equivalent to almost a month.<br /><br />Now, I'm not suggesting that the Flash is stuck in a time stream that moves much, much slower than hours and that he is always watching us continentally drift through our lives. But even so, when he's waiting in line at a supermarket, he <i>could </i>by doing something else. In fact, he could be doing, much, much more. For every instant in his stream of consciousness, he is presumably making a decision to not rush ahead and get all of everyone's shopping scanned and packed in 7.42s so he can get back to fighting crime or watching Breaking Bad or whatever it is that he actually does. Even if he has some control over how he perceives the flow of time, the crucial thing is that he always <i>knows</i> that he could be going faster if only people would just hurry up a little.<br /><br />It turns out that I am not a patient man, and that I'm indulging myself by project myself onto DC's fastest hero, albeit sans hat. I am all in favour of languorous leisure time, but I see no reason why one should dawdle when filling out forms, and can find no excuse for the person who has waited fifteen minutes in a bank queue only to arrive at the teller entirely unprepared for the experience. There is a time and a place to stop and smell the roses, and it is in a rose garden, not in your local branch of Lloyds TSB. When a dozen people behind you are on the last famished legs of their lunch break, more conscious than ever of their mortality, then one ought to push the tempo.<br /><br />But what an ugly way to live, to be always and ever mildly irked at all the poor souls who haven't put as much time and energy into learning the fastest way to use a self-checkout as I have. I don't even have to play the "well, they might have just come from the doctors with terrible news" game to see it's wrong. While it's true that you never know what's going on in someone's head, and that Fundamental Attribution Error is a real thing, and there is only one true judge, that still doesn't help me, because that still leaves some people who are slow with no excuse and in my way.<br /><br />What I need to remember are the people who've patiently waited for me to figure things out after I've made the same mistake again &amp; again, the people who've waiting for me to (literally) stop standing on their feet, to (figuratively) stop making an ass of myself, to realize exactly what it was I just said, to say sorry, for me to be sorry.<br /><br /><span style="background-color: white; color: #333333; font-family: Helvetica; font-size: 13px; text-align: justify;">This post is part of the&nbsp;</span><a href="http://life.mumak.net/2013/01/the-alphabet-supremacy.html" style="-webkit-transition: color 0.3s; background-color: white; color: #009eb8; display: inline; font-family: 'Helvetica Neue Light', HelveticaNeue-Light, 'Helvetica Neue', Helvetica, Arial, sans-serif; font-size: 13px; outline: none; text-align: justify; text-decoration: none; transition: color 0.3s;">Alphabet Supremacy</a><span style="background-color: white; color: #333333; font-family: Helvetica; font-size: 13px; text-align: justify;">&nbsp;project, a collaboration between myself and&nbsp;</span><a href="http://life.metagnome.net/" style="-webkit-transition: color 0.3s; background-color: white; color: #009eb8; display: inline; font-family: 'Helvetica Neue Light', HelveticaNeue-Light, 'Helvetica Neue', Helvetica, Arial, sans-serif; font-size: 13px; outline: none; text-align: justify; text-decoration: none; transition: color 0.3s;">Bice Dibley</a><span style="background-color: white; color: #333333; font-family: Helvetica; font-size: 13px; text-align: justify;">. He chooses next week's word.</span></div>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Office]]></title>
    <link href="http://life.mumak.net/2013/07/21/office.html"/>
    <updated>2013-07-21T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://life.mumak.net/2013/07/21/office</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<div class='post'>
The day starts with the sound of the ocean gently, steadily and, alas, digitally getting louder and louder until I can do the sums required to turn it off. &nbsp;It's followed by a lot of hot water, a few cuts to the face, a walk past a church cum Indian cultural centre cum Ingress portal before I take a short ride getting way too familiar with the sights and scents of commuters' armpits. &nbsp;If I took the slightly longer route, I'd walk past the place Gandhi lived when he was a law student, but I won't because it's hot and I'm carrying fifteen pounds of kickboxing gear on my back.<br /><br />Victoria Station is vast and frenetic. &nbsp;Everyone is in the way. &nbsp;It is impossible to not be stressed here. &nbsp;Well, maybe Gandhi could have managed it. I'm hungry and everything smells of bakery. &nbsp;I don't eat much bread these days, but that doesn't mean I don't want to leap the counter and forcefully grab a half-dozen croissants. &nbsp;The Japanese couple struggling up the stairs with suitcases twice as large as themselves misinterpret my snarl. &nbsp;I really should offer to help, but the moment passes.<br /><br />I shuffle slowly through the Tallest Glass Revolving Doors in Europe, fishing in my pocket for my ID to show to building security. &nbsp;Every time I see any security guards or bouncers these days, I wonder what it would be like to fight them. &nbsp;There's one guy here who I reckon would be vicious. &nbsp;He's small and looks maybe forty-five or fifty, but he's always weirdly alert. &nbsp;When I say "Good morning", he seems to regard it as a distraction from his watch.<br /><br />Once I'm through, I get to my floor. &nbsp;By now it's familiar to me, but I still take the time to appreciate it. &nbsp;The corridors aren't just soulless tunnels, but rich, interesting places with colour and texture. &nbsp;The deli &amp; micro-kitchens are cosy and relaxed. &nbsp;My desk maybe technically possibly counts as a cubical, but hasn't ever felt that way to me.<br /><br />The first thing I do is get coffee, which Shakespeare would have called the chief nourisher in life's feast if he only knew what he was on about. &nbsp;The coffee from the push-button machine isn't great, but it works enough to get me ready to use the espresso machine for my sophomore cup.<br /><br />I worked from home for about eight years, in one way or another, and mostly enjoyed it. &nbsp;Now I'm here, I don't miss it at all. &nbsp;Well, sometimes it's a bit noisy, but there's a beautiful, dark, quiet room where I can escape. &nbsp;The food is better, my computer is better, and the company is better.<br /><br />That is, one of the things I enjoy most about my trade is sitting around with a team, working together on something interesting. &nbsp;At my previous job, even though we worked from home mostly, we'd occasionally get together in some random city, sit in a room and hack on something for a solid week. &nbsp;Those weeks (NB:&nbsp;<i>not</i>&nbsp;the weeks where we sat around planning things) were the most fun times in a job that was overall a pretty fun job. &nbsp;So why not do that all the time?<br /><br />The day starts to wind up, I slug my kickboxing bag over my shoulder and head out. &nbsp;There's a different, friendlier security guard on duty, but I only really see his back and I think we'd both be uncomfortable if I turned around and said "Good morning". &nbsp;I get to Victoria Station, and though it shouldn't be mathematically possible there are even more people here, and they all hate me for lugging this great bloody thing around, taking up precious standing room. As I'm shoved onto the train to Euston, I can't help but think that I love this city.<br /><span style="background-color: white; font-family: Helvetica; font-size: 13px;"><br class="Apple-interchange-newline" />This post is part of the&nbsp;</span><a href="http://life.mumak.net/2013/01/the-alphabet-supremacy.html" style="background-color: white; font-size: 13px;">Alphabet Supremacy</a><span style="background-color: white; font-family: Helvetica; font-size: 13px;">&nbsp;project, a collaboration between myself and&nbsp;</span><a href="http://life.metagnome.net/" style="background-color: white; font-size: 13px;">Bice Dibley</a><span style="background-color: white; font-family: Helvetica; font-size: 13px;">. He chooses next week's word.</span></div>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
